Hey, we're back andit's intermediate ASP.NET Core 1.0,
I'm Scott Hansman.
>> I'm Jeff Fritz>> And
moving our way forward toa different sections of ASP.NET.
We talked a littleabout tag helpers and
right now let's talkabout authentication.
>> That's different fromauthorization, isn't it?
>> Yes.They call it auth-auth. Right?
>> Yeah
>> Authentication and authorization.
There's some things that are built
into ASP.NET identityout of the box.
So if we take a look here on mymachine, and I say file new project,
and I pick a core applicationby default and we hit Okay,
you see the options on the left areEmpty, Web API and Web Application,
but don't forget this button whereit says change authentication.
By default it says no auth.
>> That's the way I'd normally rule.
>> Right, there's no auth.
>> Everybody gets it.
>> Anonymous for everyone.
If you click onindividual user accounts,
you'll store user profilein a SQL database.
You can also plug in to activedirectory or Office365 or
you can use kind of Windows or
classic NTLM authentication forintranet applications.
I'm gonna clickIndividual User Accounts, all right?
I did that before.
So I'll switch over tothe one I did that on.
And you're gonna get an MVC
application that's got a little bitmore going on than typical, right?
You don't just have controller causeyou have an account controller and
a manage controller as inaddition to the home one that
we saw before, okay?
You also gonna have some databasemigration for the database.
We'll talk about those whenwe get to entity framework,
but rest assured there is one there.
Then there is the View Models.
We talked a little aboutView Models in our first day.
The View Models representthe information that is being
displayed when you login, orwhen you forget your password,
or when you need to send the codefor two factor authentication.
>> It is being massaged fromthe database to include that extra
information that youwant to display,
it is not necessary allcoming from one table.
>> Exactly.
When, if the database happento look exactly like the view,
you might bring that over, butmore often than not it doesn't.
>> Yeah.>> So
these objects hold that modelas it goes up the view.
Excellent.
And then here under services,theoretically our application could
send emails if forgot your password,or send a text message.
Those messaging servicesare encapsulated within those
interfaces.
We got our home aboutstuff that we saw before.
But we've also got manage logins andall those kinds of things.
Now we saw tag helpers, butit is worthwhile to kinda go and
look at what a fairly sophisticatedlooking page looks like.
And it is a mixture of logic andtag helpers.
>> Yeah,I'm looking at the form element now.
And that one's in purple.
And I'm seeing now that similarASP action type thing that we saw
on the anchor tag and now it'san attribute here pointing to where,
I'm guessing,we're gonna post that form back to.
>> Right, so here we're gonna go and
talk to the managed controllercalling RemoveLogIn.
We've set it up as a post, and
then we're gonna post thisform back to that controller.
Only if this particularbit of information
in the view data is seen. Okay?
Let's take a look at what this looks
like first.
All right?
So we'll hit control F5.
And we'll run our application.
I like to hit control F5.
Rather than F5, because I findthat it's faster than debugging?
>> It is?
>> Mhm.Do you do that?
>> No.
I like having the debugger attached.
I guess I'm a little bitmore insecure in my coding.
>> Interesting.>> And I want that debugger there so
that I can reach in.
>> Sure.>> And get that intermediate window
and start testing things,or bring up my watches.
Immediately.
>> Well, so speaking of debugging,here is an interesting thing I like
personally when we're doing virtualacademies and things like this that
if a mistake happen or if somethinggoes wrong I like to keep rolling.
>> Sure.>> So take a look at this,
I hit Ctrl+F5 to launch things andit launches up into this 44355,
it's on a high port andit's not loading.
So of course what do they say?
The definition of insanity is tryingthe same thing over and over.
>> Over and over again.
So hit F5.>> Well
nothing's gonna happen becauseit's obviously not working, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Now I can come down here toIIS Express though, all right.
And find out what ports is on.
Well it's on 61821,totally different port.
>> Yeah.
>> So we talked a littlebit about this before, but
it's an important reminder.
That the thing that controlsthe servers port is different
from the thing thatlaunches the browser.
>> Yeah.
>> So I have to go intolaunch settings here and
make sure that I'mdoing the right thing.
My application URL and
what URL I'm listening onare a little bit different.
What I wanna do is remember have I
turned on SSL or not.
You can actually enable SSL locallyand then have I done anything to my
application to always haveit talking over SSL and
in fact a little bit earlier as Irecall I did something like that but
what I wanna do isto turn on SSL here.
And you'll notice there isunsecure and a secure port.
>> And there is that port number,right.
>> There is port number.
Now, when I click that andhit Save and go on and run that,
Visual studio may say wouldyou like us to trust this.
This self-signed certificate.
>> Yeah.>> I'm doing this under SSL
because when I wanna domy development, I'm gonna
be posting secure passwords andstuff around.
So I wanna do it evenover kinda fake SSL.
You know what I mean?
>> Right,we wanna imitate as close to
communicating acrossthe Internet as possible.
>> Mm-hm.
So this is still not working,so it's 44355.
So I'm gonna go and confirm.
I think that number is wrong.
>> Yeah.
>> 44321.
The large settings filecontrols what gets launched.
>> Okay.>> And then here is your app URL and
here is your SSL port.
If you mess with your portmanually as I tended to
you can get those out of sync and
you get yourself in a situationthat we just got ourselves into.
So now let us give it a try.
I'm gonna run our applicationon the right port and it works.
Now to be clear,this is a SSL certificate, but
if we look at this certificate,it's localhost.
>> Yeah.>> It's a trusted certificate that
I generated and consciously trusted.
It is not a good thing.
It's just there becausewe wanna do some testing.
And additionally,when you do external logins,
they don't like to postback to insecure locations.
So if you gonna try Facebook orTwitter login,
they don't like to redirect backto local hosts without SSL.
>> Right.
The local host stuff there,
you're not gonna go outto production with this.
You are gonna have to engage andget a real SSL Certificate.
>> Absolutely, so here,I can go and put in a name and
password anddo local authentication.
So I'm gonna go andregister this locally and login.
And you'll notice that it sayscannot open this database.
>> I think this isthe coolest new little
white screen error page thatis in ASP.NET Core app.
This is really.>> Yeah, yeah.
It's not the yellow screen of death.
>> No.
>> It's the calming lightblue screen of death.
>> It's you know what?
Something's wrong here, butlet me help you fix it.
>> Yeah.So here it saying, well,
there is no identity schema, so
it's saying that the databasehas not yet been updated.
And is letting me know that Ican potentially do that here.
Or I could click apply migration andit will try to do it for me.
So the error page is tryingto fix this problem.
It may or may not work,we will find out.
Typically this can bea two steps process.
So here it says, I didthe migrations, refresh the page.
And then I could come back anddo that again.
But did it createeverything it needed to?
Make sure that that's correct.
My password skillsare well-known and epic.
For crying out loud.
That's an exampleof good validation.
>> Very good validation.
But all of the security checks foryour password are enabled.
>> It's slowing me down.
There we go.
>> There you go.
>> So now>> Now, to be clear,
those security checksare by default defined.
They're in our account controller.
>> That's a great point.
>> And you can change those tomeet your needs appropriately for
your environment if you'remanaging your own users.
>> Right.
So we're building on topof this identity user.
We can actually login to,where is our login page account?
>> Login, you can see all this.
Again, you don't want to rollyour own crypto, as they say.
But you can certainlydecided what you're password
complexity requirements are.
And all that kind of stuff.
So you have control over that.
Now look down here.
It says use anotherservice to login.
All right?And then it says, get external
authentication schemes, meaningI wanna log in with Facebook,
I wanna login with Twitter, orI wanna log in with whatever.
>> And you know what?
Facebook I think is being able tologin with Facebook to another
application is so valuable.
Because there are people like,I talk about my parents, or
my mother-in-law.
Who they have their Facebook IDs.
They wanna be able to just getinto that next application.
Without having to go createanother user ID and password.
>> Yep, absolutely.
Actually we made an acronym,
non gender specificnon technical parent.
>> Okay.>> And
my parents are like that as well.
And if my dad can log in withFacebook, then he is happy.
So, on the right hand side it says.
There are no externalauthentication services configured.
What made that?
That's this.
SignInManager says,are there any other login providers?
You can register login providerswith ASP.NET, and it's all built in.
What's nice about this is that thereis an article set up to do that.
So, why don't we,rebels that we are, click on that.
And try to enablesome Facebook logins.
Shall we?
>> Sure.>> You can also see that,
by the way, if we go into Startup,let's try this.
Let's just explore this just brieflybefore we get started actually.
So, here's our Startup, we've gotour app settings, that's cool.
There's gonna be this UserSecrets.
They're not really secret ina sense of they're encrypted.
They're just not inthe current folder.
>> They're not inthe current folder.
They're hidden so that you can'taccidentally check them into GitHub.
>> Right.
So, UserSecrets are meant so
that you don't hurt yourselfby checking in secret things.
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> Like the key that we'regonna use to log into Facebook.
>> Right.
>> Okay, but they are not->> It's not like we're gonna publish
that in a video thateverybody's gonna see.
>> Right, exactly,you would never do that.
>> No.
>> So, then we've got ourdatabases and EntityFramework.
And we'll hear about thata little bit later today.
>> A little bit later.
>> Yup, okay.
We've got some logging middlewarethat we'll learn about as well.
But then we just have UseIdentity().
That's what we just did.
We logged in as me.
Local database.
Local everything.
Worked great.
That's identity.
External authenticationmiddleware will happen below.
We're gonna take this link here andfollow that. Okay?
So, here's our social logins.
So, what we need todo is go to Facebook,
to developers.facebook.apps.
We'll use Facebook but we coulduse Twitter or whatever, okay?
So, I will go andadd a new app, okay?
Add a website.
And we'll call it the MVA app.
Create a new Facebook ID.
Category, Entertainment,I have no idea.
Okay, this is fun.
Select all the photosthat show a lion.
That's a nice watch.
Hopefully, I am still a real person.
All right, they're tellingus about our Facebook SDK.
I don't need the Quick Start.
Tell us about your website, right?
So, where is our website?
We're gonna skip some of this stuff.
Because all I really care about isthe fact that I'm on localhost at
this point.
I wonder if they'll care.
localhost.
>> Some of those things that you'reskipping are things to configure.
So, that when folks visitthe application on Facebook and
they learn->> Exactly.
>> About the application there,
it's information to givethem context on Facebook.
>> Exactly,what I really need to get
this done is I need my App ID,and my App Secret.
The problem is Facebook changestheir UI, every 20 minutes.
So, you don't always getthe same stuff that you expect.
So, here is my App ID.
>> It's also in the header there,on that page.
>> Excellent, click to copy.
I'll put that, thank you.
We'll put that in Notepad.
And then our App Secret,
ooh is there.
So, I'm gonna getboth of these things.
Secret.
And then the App ID.
This can be revoked later.
That's why you generate an app.
You can say, well,that app went rogue.
So, someone compromised it.
I'm gonna revoke that.
Then people would no longer be ableto log in with Facebook, okay.
And then we could
actually see Login Users withpeople using Facebook log in.
So, that would be useful.
Cool, so we made a note of ourApp ID and our App Secret.
And then we can add in our site URL.
Now the secret management, right?
We have to getthe Secret Manager tool.
We should probably already have thaton this particular application.
Let's give it a try.
So, what I'm gonna do is I'm gonnaopen up this particular folder and
get the path.
Cuz I wanna know wherethis website is, right?
And do I come out here to the,I like to call it the DOSBox,
but it's the Command Prompt.
cd over into that location.
>> Yeah.
>> Andremember the .NET command line.
I should be able to saydotnet user-secrets.
Okay, .NET's gonna do sometidying up because I cleared
my caches earlier.
>> So, it's reconfiguring.
>> It's repopulating my cache.
It just takes one second.
It's a local package cache,doesn't have to happen very often.
Let me do that again,dotnet user-secrets.
So, that is the user secretsutility that is installed here.
Where is that installed, right?
>> Yeah, this is a tool thatwe really don't want to be
used when we deploy.
>> Mm-hm, right,it's not a dependency, it's a tool.
So, it's a thing we would use likeentity framework migrations or
code generation.
These are things that are tools notshipped when you go to production.
>> Yup.
>> Okay?
So, we go over here,we have the UserSecrets tool.
Being able to typedotnet user-secrets.
The ability to be able to type thatis predicated on that being there.
If it wasn't there,we couldn't do that.
Okay, soit says .NET user-secrets, app ID.
We'll pullover the notebook,a Notepad rather.
So, would it look like this,all right?
You see?
And then the app-secretwould look like This
I don't want to accidentally removeone of those characters, all right.
So now,>> You could run those commands
>> We could run those commands, exactly
>> To the secret store,
where is the secret store?
>> It's like a spyhiding your stuff.
>> Where is the secret store anyway?
>> Actually you can see this secret.
If you go back to Visual Studio.
>> Okay>> There's a neat trick here you
can use to find.
If you right click onweb application there is
a manage user secretsitem down here.
Click that.
>> My goodness.
>> And now there's the itemsyou just keyed in.
>> That's somehow less secretthat I thought it would be.
>> But check it out,here you just mouse over the tab and
there's the entire folder locationof where this file lives.
It's not in your application,
it's hanging out inthis GUID folder name.
>> Right, again notthe intention to encrypt it.
>> No.>> Not the intention to make it
secure but rather make it secret.
>> It's secret->> You don't check it in.
>> Yeah, you don't check it in, it'ssecret in that you as a developer
Own this information, andit needs to be clear and
available for you as a developer tobe able to change and update later.
>> Right.
All right.
So.
We've got, if it's in development,you use secrets.
Let's make sure thatthat's in there.
This is in Startup We haven't gotthat, so we're in development mode.
Actually, I think it'sup in the constructor.
Let's try that.
Pardon me, you're absolutely right.
So, that's part of configuration.
So, we grab our configurationfrom app settings,
user sequence is a kindof configuration.
If it's not in development We needto put those in a proper secret
store and there are thingslike Azure Key Vault.
>> Yes.
>> Other places forproduction secrets.
>> They may set up thingswith a PowerShell script so
that they get loaded as environmentvariables there on line 34.
>> And my environment variableswould be totally appropriate
if it wasn't super secret.
>> Yeah.>> You could go and
use this in something like Azure and
set it up as an environment variableand it would just be available.
>> Yes.
>> Excellent.The point is Don't put them in
your code.
So now, we're gonna go andgrab NewGit and we're gonna get
the Microsoft ASP.NET coreFacebook authentication package.
Now again, I can go andmanually edit but
I also kind of like to use this.
The user interface.
>> The user interface.
It is just nice now.
I cannot like it.
I am going back and forth.
So, here I go.Here
is the core middle ware for these.
We go and say install.
This is going to bring thatpackage down for Facebook and
then whatever additionalstuff is required.
You will notice down hereit is getting all worth
which is independency.
Of the Facebook.
So, it's grabbing those tools,grabbing those things that we need.
And it's now done.
Excellent.
Okay, soremember how we had app.UseIdentity.
What we need to do isadd those external
Authentication middleware is there.
It's all about middleware.
We're gonna dig a little bit moreinto middleware in a little bit.
There's using it whichis what we're doing.
>> Yep.And then there's making it which is
what you're gonna teach me about.
>> Yeah, we're gonna take a lookat some interesting things you
can do there.
>> So, I'll paste that in.
>> Conveniently rightnext to the note. Yeah.
How fun is that?
So this string right there,we confirmed,
is the name value pair that youcan find when you right-click and
say manage user secrets.
It's that string.
So then if I had Twitter or Steam or
any other log-in provider, thesecrets would show up there as well.
And they just get passed in.
In this case, Facebook auth,I'd have Twitter auth and
I'd have different things.
If you have your own auth,you can write your own middleware.
>> Yes.
>> And participate in identity.
>> Okay.
>> So now, let's go andrun the thing.
And find out ifFacebook Authentication
enlisted itself as an externallog in provider, okay.
Let's see go and run.
Fire it up.
Million things couldgo wrong right now.
>> Hold my breath.
>> Well this is the thing now.
When you do demos, you don't tryto do them so that they work.
People think that when youcreate a demo, you write a demo,
that you're intending forit to work on the first try.
>> Right.>> I like things to break.
Because I think that that'sa learning opportunity.
>> Absolutely it is.
>> So we see here,use another service to log on.
>> And now Facebook is available.
>> Before we do that and prove itworks, because we don't know yet
that it works.
Let's make sure that we can confirmthat we know what's happening.
So, I'm on Account/Login, all right?
And if you look right here, getexternal authentication's schemes.
I'm assuming now thatthere is one of those.
>> Take a look.
>> Four each.
And it generated our submit button.
>> Generated our button,but look at this here.
You see it says value,
log in to your provider.DisplayNameaccount, right?
>> Yeah, very cool.
>> It is nice.
Let's give it a try.
So check it out.
We've automatically showed upover to my personal Facebook, and
it says this app will get yourprofile and your email address, and
this is really important.
This doesn't let the apppost to Facebook.
>> Yeah.
>> A little details.
>> Those security restrictions>> Mm-hm.
>> That are defined there are so
important that a lotof people over looked.
>> They really do,they just click through.
And this is nice, Facebook log in,isn't a Facebook app permissions,
because in the old daysit felt like anything
could potentially post to Facebook.
>> Right.>> But now somehow we just wanna
log in.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So we'll say continue.
And then look at that it redirectedbecause we had told Facebook
the URL.
I came back, andthese is really interesting.
Checked this out.
Associate your Facebook account.
Let's see, I already have an accountthat we'd logged in on earlier.
If I hit register,it's say you've already taken.
So that kinda stinks.
>> [LAUGH]>> I'll put in another account.
I shouldn't have loggedin Facebook before.
And now, there I am.
>> Cool.
Very cool.
>> Andthis means that we can log in and
out to this application withoutit seeing our password.
See?
I hit log off, hit log in.
Log in with Facebook.
Does the little bounce.
And then I'm back.
>> Yeah, that little bounce iskinda important right there.
There's actually severalcommunications that are going on
there back and fort.
>> That's a great point.
>> Facebook, our application andthe browser.
>> Mm-hm.That's a good point.
Let's look at that real quick.
I'm just gonna say record networkactivity, and I'll hit log in.
And what I'm gonna do isremove images and CSS and
we'll just take with Java script and
things that matternot the data stuff.
Java script, I want that Iwant cross side scripting.
I want some Java script, I want somedocuments, I want to move services.
And I'm gonna say, log in Facebook.
Oops, one of the things that'sinteresting when you're trying to
record traffic like this.
You notice that it popped.
It showed me and then it cleared it.
You have to go andsay, preserve log.
Don't clear the log on page re-load.
One of the little details thatyou just learn after time.
Let's go ahead andlog off, log in, Facebook.
That was quick.
Interestingly, I feel like it didn'tdo a good job of representing that.
Because if you look down here,here's external login, it's 302.
Here's Facebook oauth.
>> Right.>> With all my and stuff
>> 302 then it went localhost
signin Facebook.
So it went all the way to Facebook,got some stuff, jump back over, gave
me the result, 302 back to itself,and then launch the main page.
To your right,
there is a dance there what feelslike one click is like five.
>> Right.It's just important to be
aware of that.
As you are programming these thingsif you're expecting something else
to happen in there.
>> Or if you want to try andmanage that process,
you don't have control of that.
That's the securityof your application.
>> Yep, exactly.
So that is kind of an overviewof identity login.
We saw that we can have thatidentity stored in a local database.
>> Yep.>> We can associate, and
number of external logins,in this case Facebook.
And if you follow those tutorials,and
there's lots of greattutorials on docs.asp.net.
Things will mostly work.
But when they don't,it's not a black box.
>> It's not.
There's ways to solve this.
There's a number of websitesout there from other folks in
the community that havewritten providers and
written documentation abouthow to use those providers.
I particularly wanna callout ooffforaspnet.com.
Check that one out.
There's all kinds of providers for
many of these services that youuse for other applications.
>> Absolutely andit's not just Facebook and Twitter.
>> Nope.>> It's Windows Live, it's Steam.
>> Steam.
>> It's Orange, anyone thatOAuth linked in you can have, so
if your application needsa particular thing.
They should have middleware thatsome on the community has made.
Or because it's building on OF,
ultimately you just have to figureout what the URL schemes are.
All right.
>> Cool.
>> So that is doingauthentication middleware.
We'll take a short break andwe'll come right back.