Hi, I'm Scott Hanselman.
And I'm Jeff Fritz.
And this isIntermediate ASP.NET Core 1.0.
If you made it here somehowto the middle of our day.
And you don't know how you got here.
You might take a look atthe beginner ASP.NET Core that
we did before.
It's a whole day ofgreat beginner content.
Yep.
So what we're gonna be talkingabout right now is this idea of
middleware.
Yeah, it feels like a loaded term,middleware.
It's software that's inthe middle of something.
It is.And
it's not really clear where it fits,how it works and
what it means to people who arewriting ASP.NET code that maybe in
the past had written handlers ormodules, right?
It's a different concept.
Right.
In the old days,last week before the new stuff.
There was this concept of the HTTPhandler and the HTTP module.
Handlers of course were an endpoint,and
modules were the I'mlistening at all times.
Yeah, right, and there wasthis concept of events, right?
And everything was event driven and
that you had all these modulesthat were out there and
when an event fired whether it wasa net, load, pre-render, unload,
it would trigger all of the modulesthat were listening for that event.
So you could have all thesethings happen at the same time.
We're now middleware, well,
it's more of a pipeline than thisabstract event listening thing.
Exactly, before you would havesomething like begin request and
then we'd all listeninto the begin request.
And everyone would get anopportunity to mess up the system.
But with middleware,it is a pipeline.
If you take a look at thisdiagram on my screen right here.
This is from the documentationat docs.asp.net.
This is a really great diagram thatgives you this idea that it is,
it's a pipeline but it's also kindof a chain, and order matters.
If you learn one thingabout middleware, and
we'll hear about it when youshowed me some custom middleware,
that the order of thatmiddleware matters so much.
You have some logic and
then you have a chain to the nextmiddleware and you say next.
And you pass your controlto the next middleware,
and it goes all the way tothe end until it terminates.
And then it rolls all the way back,all right?
So we've got my sillylittle application here.
This was the one that we did.
In the beginner asp.net core we werejust talking about the basics of
MVC.
All this application doesis basically nothing.
[LAUGH] It has a silly little model,and it returns it to the view.
So it's a little bitmore than hello world.
If we look at start up, it has,
the configure in our startuphas basically the MVC services.
We've got our hosting environmentand our logging, so there's logging.
We've got an environment check fordevelopment.
And then we sayUseDeveloperExceptionPage.
Now there were two differentconfigure methods there.
We should touch on what thosetwo different methods do.
Because they do twodifferent things.
Right, ConfigureServices isconfiguring dependency injection.
We'll talk a little bitmore about that later on
in the intermediate date here.
But this configure methodthat starts on line 36,
this is where we're laying outour middleware pipeline, right.
Right, it's almost sketching ordrawing the pipeline and
it's setting the tone forthe rest of it.
It's saying it looks like this,it is in this order.
And if you saw in our discussionof authentication and
authorization, we had identityappearing within there.
And it appearedbefore UseMvc because
it was something that wouldhappen ahead of time.
And we had to configure Facebook asa provider after identity was added.
Mm-hm, so what happens if we go anddo something silly here?
I'm just gonna say app.Run.
Remember that app.Run() iskind of the terminating bit of
middleware there.
It's gonna say I'm gonna do all ofthat work and I'm gonna take over.
Let's say context, and
I'm gonna say throw_new,I'm gonna cheat here.
We're gonna force an error, okay?
Invalid operation exception.
Okay?
So there's a little bit of and
we go and we go.
Sometimes these things can geta little bit confusing and
I'll find myself adding asmany of these as possible.
I actually forgot one there.
Yeah, there you go.
See, I just go like this andjust- Eventually it works out.
Eventually it'll work. Yeah.
Exactly, but
actually that's a good point.
It can be a little bit confusing.
Let's talk about that.
Notice how when I move my mouseover these braces or parentheses.
It's lighting up the pair, so,right, if I click here you can see.
It's showing you where it began, andit's showing you the closing one,
the matching pair. Exactly.
So, there's open, there's there and
then this extra stuff here,I don't know what I was thinking,
not really what we needed.
Not needed but no foul, no harm.
No foul, exactly, sohere we're gonna throw an exception.
Is this ever gonna getthe opportunity to happen?
No, because that app runit is as you said it is
a terminating piece of middle ware.
It is not passingcontrol on to the next.
From our diagram there isa next call that happens,
we are not calling next herewithin that, within your app run.
So it's gonna stop,
after it's done running thispiece of code on line 49.
All right, and in fact,let me remove that and
run our app and just see whatit does kind of by default here.
Oops, it's saying that the app isbeing used by another process.
That is because I amnot running under IIS.
I'm running under Kestrel,remember we switch those ways here,
we talked about thaton beginner day.
So I'm gonna just shut that down andrun it again.
Look at that, nothing. Nothing.
Nothing.
Not even informationabout that error?
Not even informationabout that error.
If we look over here In our log.
Yeah, in our logs.
I see a big red fail there.
Right.
There's our exception.
But, so I'm getting information,I'm finding out what's going on.
I got my info, I got my fail,I got my call stack,
including the line number cuzI'm doing a debug here, but
I didn't get anything friendlyfrom a web perspective.
And let's even look andsee what happened, what do I get?
I'm getting, look,I'm getting a 500 error, right?
400 is your fault, 500 is my fault.
So, remember what you would see inASP.NET in the past when you did
that, right, you would get-The yellow screen of doom.
Right, or
the yellow screen of death,the yellow screen of doom, exactly.
You get that big yellowscreen with ASP.NET Core.
It's important to remember thatnothing's included by default,
you have to ask forit if you want it.
So we want to bring that back,that thing that I removed.
If we're in the developmentenvironment,
use the developer exception page.
So that's effectively usethe yellow screen of death
Is what that's saying That'sa piece of middleware.
We can actually zoom in on that,see.
Captures exceptions instances.
That is what that for and thengenerates an html error response.
Now, it is somethingyou had to opt into.
But there may be some environmentswhere they don't want this running.
And that's why we're saying,
is development,is this the development environment.
By default we're not includingthis capability when you get to
production.
Right, a production errormessage could still happen.
But it should not probablyinclude my source code. No.
Right.
No, no.Where is this coming from?
That lives inside ofAspNetCore.Diagnostics.
So it's that diagnostics packagethat is making that possible.
Makes sense.
Okay, so let's run it again now.
Except we're gonna includeUseDeveloperExceptionPage.
Notice that the loggingstill happens.
Yeah, we still see those fail logs.
And that's totally fine.
And that will eithergo into the console or
Visual Studio's output window. Sure.
Mm-hm, or in the case of Azure,
it'll go into Storage or whereverwe've decided to put our tracing.
However you configureyour logging provider.
Mm-hm, so
this as we said before is thepeaceful light blue screen of death.
Yeah, it's kind of nice though.
You can see the raw details.
You can see a rendering of it.
Yeah that block at the bottomlooks more like what I expect
out of Visual Studiowhen I get a stack tray.
Yeah it's interestingthat you say that,
because that kind of unfriendlything is what you would expect, but
in fact look at this You're gettingthe exact line of code, you can
see the Queries and the Cookies,see the culture, I can see Headers.
So, you're getting a nice experiencehere but here's the important part.
Maybe this isn't whatyour company wants,
maybe you want yourown screen of death.
Let say that you’re doingproducts and shopping carts.
Maybe shopping cart information'simportant to your exception page.
Why not add shopping carts?
Or Identity, or OAuth, orwhatever makes you happy?
Before, do you know wherethe L-screen of death lived,
like on disk, where was it?
I couldn't even point to it.
>> Gosh.
>> It was in the beast.
It was hiding in a .dll somewhere,compiled and strong-named and,
Hidden in the beast,the GAC somewhere under C:Windows.
>> Exactly, somewhere in the GlobalAssembly Cache there was a yellow
screen of death thatyou could never change.
Additionally, lots of peoplewent to production, and
we've all had that experience,where we go to a webpage and
then you like,wow I'm looking at source code.
And you get that kind of like,nobody's supposed to be here,
this not okay.
>> Yeah, this feels dirty.
>> Right, so
the problem here is that we shippedthat with the wrong defaults.
So in this case,
you don't get an exceptionpage unless you asked for it.
And if you specifiedthe appropriate environment.
So then the question is, what wouldthis look like for production.
What do we wanna do?
So let's say,if it's development, do this.
Else it's anything but development.
So then we can write a littlepiece of middleware here.
And if I understand correctly,
we don't need to write middlewarenecessarily, with its own class.
>> No, you can use an anonymousobject there in the middle.
>> Sowe'll say app.UseExceptionHandler,
adds a middleware to the pipelineto catch exceptions, logs them.
And then re-execute the request,in an alternate pipeline.
>> Okay.
>> So we're gonna say,ExceptionHandler and then we're not
gonna use app,we're gonna use, subApp.
So this is an alternate pipeline,
because the one that's brokenis ruined for us at this point.
So, we're gonna go here andwe're gonna say subApp.Run.
And try to do some stuff.
>> You've got a minus there.
>> You think that's a problem?
>> That's a start.
>> You think I couldjust go like that?
That would be coolif that was a thing.
>> It's like the flaming arrow.
>> Yeah, sometimes I callit the hash rocket, but
I like to refer to thatas the Anders operator.
>> Sure.
>> Yeah,context.Response.ContentType,
this is really low level stuff.
Notice I'm not sending it off,I could, but
I'm not sending it off to an HTMLpage, a static page on disk.
>> But you are literally handcrafting, the HTTP response.
>> Yeah, not super friendly andnot super fun, but
at the same time super powerful anduseful to know that it's possible.
>> Yeah,full control over all the things.
>> Exactly,now this is going to be our
production one, you don'twanna have any errors in here.
>> Sure, and that's exactly theproduction message we want to send,
on 53 [LAUGH].
>> And here's a little funnypiece of history here.
Internet Explorer,has some issues with short errors.
So if the error happens, and
the html page is shorter than about5, 600 bytes, it won't show it.
>> Are you kidding?
>> Yeah, it is what it is.
>> Okay.>> So we're gonna make a new string,
and we're gonna put 512 spaces,just for IE.
A little bit of context.
Life happens, comes at you fast.
But what we really care about,is up here.
Maybe we'll want tosay something like,
Application Error in Production.
Contact Support.
Something like that.
This, SubApp,
happens within thatExceptionHandler.
Let's make sure this is a littlebit of fun as we try to figure out.
>> Make sure things are lined up.
>> Do I need that?
I need that.
There we go,let's see if that builds.
>> There's an extra.
You need a paren.
>> Paren, because all of that is.
Well, that one got dropped down,there we go.
>> Yeah, there it is.
>> Well this isactually interesting.
The fact that I'm having troubledoing that, kind of shows that at
some point I'm gonna wanna graduate->> To something a little bit more
sophisticated.
>> To putting maybe that in a class,because that, I enjoy doing,
app.Use this and I go app.Use,I like using all this stuff.
This is great, look at that,Use middleware, how do I do that?
Why do this?
But that's fine.
Use ExceptionHandler isa middleware helper, and
I'm passing it what I want it to do.
>> Right, and like you said,
you're in a new instance of anotherpipeline that's being retried.
You have the exact same run syntax,
that you have little bit furtherdown there on lines 59 through 62.
>> So while it might bea little bit overwhelming,
you eventually figure it out.
>> Yeah.
>> So this though,happens in development.
This happens in production.
So I'm gonna have tochange my environment,
to indicate that weare in Production.
So let's give this a try,and see what happens.
Look at that.
>> Nice.
>> That happened.
Let me try it on Internet,do I have Internet Explorer?
Make sure it worked.
Cool.
>> Works just fine there too.
>> Works great.
Now, notice this though.
The log still happened,the error still happened,
it's just that I chose to show itto the user in a different way.
In this context I could then,send it off to raygun.ao, or
Application Insights, or
a third party applicationmanagement company.
>> Sure, at this point you're onlywriting to the response here on
those lines.
You can absolutely jump off,send a text message,
send notification tomy login provider.
>> Well, and that's why youhave logger factories, and
we saw at the very end of thebeginner discussion, where we added
like serial log, a third partylogger we could plug it in,
even a logger for slack or HipChat.
So, lot's of opportunities there.
Now in this case here,we're returning a 500 error.
But I might also wanna return otherthings, I might wanna understand,
how can I make a custom pageif there's a 404, for example.
So this exception here,this, I forced an exception.
Let us force a 404.
I could maybe make a file andthen, not ask for it.
But because we are done here,at the HTTP level,
I'm gonna show you that we can goand say, I wanna return a 404.
And then we have to goan say don't do anything.
So 404, we're forcing a 404, our appnow only knows how to say nothing.
>> Saying, file not found.
>> Yes, that's the only thingour app knows how to use.
This is officially the most uselessapp, that is possibly out there.
And it doesn't even say anything fora 404, it's the lonely and
sad blank 404.
Same kind of thing,this UseExceptionHandler idea,
I can go and say register,just like we registered our
ExceptionHandler there, I couldsay not use ExceptionHandler.
But I could say UseStatusCodePages.
And then in here,we could say NOT FOUND!
It's not you it's me.
By saying, UseStatusCodePages andthen passing in that
additional sub pipeline, that givesme control over what I decide to do.
For each of these errors,and that can be any error.
In this case,see what that looks like.
>> Terrific>> Custom 404.
>> Simple.
>> Very nice.
But again,had to do a little bit of work here.
And I didn't really manipulate,the custom middleware.
I understand, that you havean example that's a little more
sophisticated.
>> Yeah, we can get a littlebit more sophisticated on my
machine now.
We're gonna take a look->> So let's take a second, and
lets switch over to your box, andsee what's going on in your machine.
>> So we've seen a number ofthings here with the environment,
and we're changingthe environment and
different thingshappen on the screen.
So, I wanna actually startputting information about,
what environment I'm in onthe screen as a little indicator,
a little image sothat I know that I'm in development.
I'm in staging or I'm in production.
So I'm gonna start off,
I'm gonna show you somecode that we wrote here.
I wanna use syntax, like this,UseEnvironmentDisplay.
>> Okay, so we did tag helpers,I could go and make one,
that output the environment.
But I'd probably,have to do that on every page.
>> Right, you'd have toinclude that everywhere.
By making some middleware,
that includes that environment labeleverywhere, it automatically gets
processed in the pipeline as wehit that, during processing.
>> I see, so I've got a pieceof diagnostics middleware,
as opposed to something I'd addto my layout page in my view.
>> Exactly, it's always there and
when I don't need it,I can comment it out.
Or, as I'll show you in a littlebit, I've actually written it so
it reads a configuration option,and will activate appropriately.
So this Use middleware display,
it's an extension method usingthat same Use Syntax that.
>> So when you go app., if youzoom in on that, each of those,
yeah zoom in on those,you can see that each of the uses.
>> There they are.
>> They all have that little downarrow, they've been spot-welded onto
the app object, and that's whenuser environment display showed
up because you declared itas an extension method.
>> I declared it asan extension method and
all I did was create anotherclass out here that just
houses some middlewareextension methods.
So here I have userenvironment display,
I paste in that application builder,right, that's this app thing.
>> You said this, IApp, that'sthe syntax for an extension method.
And what's funny about this isthat this is a nothing method.
>> Exactly.
>> It's one line.
>> Right.>> This makes me feel like
you could probably justsay app.UseMiddleware.
>> Absolutely, but this gives methat little bit of syntactic sugar
that I can just say app.Use and
go find that named piece ofmiddleware that I like to use.
>> Syntactic sugar,or syntactic Splenda.
>> Sure,depending on your dietary needs.
>> I'm just saying.
>> Just saying.
>> Okay.>> All right.
>> So then use middlewareenvironment display,
that's where the real work is.
>> That's where the real work is.
So I wrote this environmentdisplay class and
it's actually a pretty simple class,
I don't have to inherit from somebase class to write middleware.
>> Really it's just a plain object.
>> It's just a plain object,the only requirement
is that you havea task invoke method.
So this is an async task invokethat's going to receive,
it always receives the HTTP context
when the pipeline wants to invokethis particular piece of middleware.
>> I see, so kind of thinkingback to that image as you're
going in the chain, when it'syour turn and they say next and
then you have to think about[CROSSTALK] of context.
>> You got it, the constructor,
I'm receiving a number ofinput parameters here,
a request delegate forwhat the next item in the chain is.
So this is called when the chain isbeing built, so it's giving me some
information as to who's nextthat I'm going to call.
And I'm also grabbing someinformation about the hosting
environment and my configuration.
>> Andthis is using dependency injection,
you're getting those because you putthem in the method signature, and
we'll learn about thatin another module.
>> Yep, yep, so I'm stashing themin some read-only fields here on
lines 19 through 21.
And then I'm goingto come down here,
I have an is enabled checkhere to say if there's
an environment display set in myconfiguration, grab that value,
otherwise don't displaythe environment, it's false.
So by default I'm going to turnit on inside my configuration.
But let's actually take a lookat the invoke where I'm actually
working with the middleware here,writing and
interacting with that context.
So the first things I'm doinghere is I'm grabbing the actual
HTML from my glyph that Iwanna drop on the response.
I have a pair of helper methods downhere that all they do is generate
some CSS style to add to the head,and
then the actual div that I'm gonnadrop on the body of my page.
>> I see, now are these gonnabe all together in one section?
>> No, they're not.
I wanna put my head elements here,my CSS stuff, up in the top inside
the head of my page, because we likeour styles to be inside the head so
they get processed nicely.
But then I'm gonna add this elementat the very bottom of my page, so
that it gets added on to everypage right before the body tag,
the close body tag that is, okay.
So I'm adding them intwo different places.
Now returning backhere to the processing,
I grab a reference to the currentcontext response body.
So as the HTTP pipeline ishappening, I'm gonna go and
get a copy of what's been addedto the response at this point.
>> That's not, and I'm curious,that's not super efficient right?
>> Not, it's not.
>> This isn't somethingyou'd go to production with.
>> No.>> I mean, with respect,
isn't this technique, it's a littleaggressive in the sense of you are,
like you said you'rejust making a copy.
>> Yeah.>> So
that kinda tells me that middlewarecan both do good and evil.
>> Absolutely, right?
>> Yeah, you could write middlewarethat isn't efficient, that uses
a lot of memory, but runs a regularexpression on the entire body.
>> Gosh yes, yeah.
>> Okay, so all right, this is justa sample to show how some of these
things work, it's not optimized.
>> Understood, butit is very powerful.
>> Absolutely, and
we're gonna see some of thathere in this next couple lines.
So I create a memory stream thereon 57, of course using a using
statement so we release ourmemory when we're done.
>> I'm gonna get a copy of,
I'm gonna put my memorystream back into the context.
So now I'm receiving what's goingto be written into my response
in my memory stream soI can analyze that content.
Typically response is a stream thatyou can't scan through and modify.
So andthen I do this await next, right
this is that delegate that we gotpassed up here in the constructor.
It says here's the next thingto execute in the pipeline,
so execute those next things, go allthe way through until you terminate,
get to that MVC action method.
>> Sothe entire page finishes its job?
>> Right, it's done renderingall of its HTML and
it's placed it on the response body,
which as we know is now ourmemory stream that we control.
>> All right, soI've now intercepted and
captured that content.
So now on 64, I'm gonna put the old,
the previous body that was alreadythere back onto the response.
Make sure that I'm working withan actual HTML output right,
I don't wanna go andintercept JavaScript or CSS.
And then I'm gonna write backinto that, if it's not HTML,
I'm gonna write out whatexactly was output.
The real interception here andthe power that we're gonna do,
I'm just doing a string
variable here to grab that contentthat was written into that stream.
And then I'm gonna insertmy CSS at the top,
right before the end head tag.
And then, I'm gonna replacethe body tag with my div and
the end body tag, andthen write that back out.
So I've intercepted, modified thecontent, and written it all back out
all in one shot here,in couple dozen lines of code.
>> Yeah.>> So not bad, if I run this now and
we can actually take a lookat how we're modifying.
This is the default projectthat comes with Visual Studio.
>> Okay, so the only thing you'vedone is add your middleware and
said use.
>> And use that, right.
And now I get my little glyph here,
this little deer thatsays it's developed.
>> The development deer.
>> That's the development deer.
So I can go andchange my configuration over here.
I can turn that off by flipping myconfiguration and if I restart.
>> And you could also perhapsset your configuration
to reload on change.
>> Yes, yep.
>> We saw that inan earlier module as well.
>> Now that's interesting,
it didn't pick it up even though Iset environment display to false.
>> Did you restart?
>> I believe I clickedRestart over here.
Let's take a quick look.
There is a check here.
>> Let's look at your check foryour config.
>> You know what?
>> I think it might be where->> I'm not actually doing the check
for the config,I have this is enabled here.
>> But you never checked for it.
>> And I never checked for it.
>> So then, if you're in the middleof this and you wanted to go and
check for it,you should probably check for
it really early on before you doany of that memory stream stuff.
>> Before I do any of thatstuff just let it go and
do its await next.
>> So if it's not enabledthen you just await next?
>> So let's just do that right here.
>> And then [CROSSTALK].>> If not is enabled I can say await
next, pass the context, and return.
>> Has it returned task is zero?
>> You're right.
>> Task.from result.
>> From result.
>> What's it say?
What's it say?
>> It's telling me that a returnkeyword must be followed by
an object expression.
>> Return await?
Do you return the next?
Do you return await next?
>> You know what,let's just do that.
And restart.
>> No.>> Nope, didn't like it.
>> Rather than returning remove thatreturn and then just fall through.
So if it's enabled else,and then do the rest of it.
>> That make sense, okay.
>> All right,let's see if that works.
>> And build.
>> Cuz when your configuration isset up right you wanna do as little
as possible if not nothing.
>> Sure, there it goes.
>> I like development deer,it's like ship it squirrel.
>> It is, there's actuallya whole family of the deer there.
>> And there you go.>> And there we go.
>> Very cool.
>> So there's several other deerthere that when you have different
environments it'll show youthose images appropriately.
So it's a simple piece of middlewarethat's showing how we can do this
great power, modifying that content,that HTML that's being output.
You can also change this sothat your managing and outputting
images or other binary contentappropriately for your application.
There's a lot you can do here andwe're just scratching the surface.
>> Middleware is fundamentalto ASP.NET Core.
>> It is.
MVC, the pattern MVC,is itself middleware.
>> It's a collection of middleware,Identity is middleware.
Everything is this middlewarepipeline concept, whether it be
a tiny piece of middlewarethat maybe logs something, or
squirrels away a request ID, or
it's something big thatfundamentally modifies the HTML.
There's a lot of power there,and of course measure and
test to make surethe performance is appropriate.
>> Yes.
>> But super powerful stuff.
So we'll take a little break andwe'll come right back.