Hi, I'm Scott Hanselman.
>> And I'm Jeff Fritz.
>> And this isIntermediate ASP.NET Core 1.0.
We've covered a numberof different topics.
Be sure to explore all ofthe different things going on
today in thisMicrosoft Virtual Academy.
Right now, we're talkingabout dependency injection.
>> It's a big couple of words,but it really breaks
down into something that's easy tounderstand when you look at it.
>> Yeah, there's subtletiesto dependency injection.
But for the most part, the way Ilike to think about it is I'm gonna
spend less time new'ing up something>> I say that, I say new'ing it up.
Like as you look throughyour ASP.net core code,
you won't find yourself saying,new this and new that as much.
>> Right.
They say new is glue, right?
As soon as you say new something,
you're hooked into the signatureof a constructor for that object.
>> Well that's good.
We use that. Yeah.
>> Go for it.
>> Did you make that up?
>> No.>> All right, we're gonna take that.
>> We're gonna have to thankSteve Smith for that one.
>> Yeah?>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, I like that, new as glue.
So dependency injection and
then they also call itinversion of control.
>> Yes.>> Another way of saying
let someone else be responsible forcreating that.
And in the past we wouldhave like factories and
that was an attempt at lettingsomeone else be responsible.
We would have an interface andthen we would have an i factor,
dah dah dah, andit would make stuff.
But really what dependency injectionis about is saying, it is my intent
that I need these things, I declarethe need for these objects.
>> Yes, yes.>> I need these interfaces.
I don't care how I get them.
I just need to make sure thatby the time I get called,
that they have arrived andthat they've been setup.
>> Somebody else take responsibilityfor creating them and
passing them to me.
>> Well said.
>> So let's switch overto my machine here and
take a look at a couple of examplesof dependency injection and
then we'll try to create somethingof our own because a few moments ago
in the previous module,did some discussion of middle-ware.
>> Yes.>> We'll do another piece of
middle-ware that then usesdependency injection and
we'll see how itaffects its behavior.
All right, so here one of the thingsthat we wanna point out as we
keep coming back to Startup.
Startup has this iHostingenvironment that's
being passed in onthe constructor there.
Who makes that?
Nowhere in this applicationhas someone said
var x equals newhosting environment.
That's getting handedin by the system.
The system has handed me that,right?
>> Yeah.It's one of those things that
the framework takes care of foryou and it just arrives for you.
For the most part,
for the intermediate level thatyou're working with the framework,
it's just handed to you.
[CROSSTALK]>> Baked in to ASP.net.
So if I wanted an ILoggerFactoryhere, I would just add it.
And I can have this parameterlist in a method or
in this case, in a constructor, bein whatever order, doesn't matter,
and I can name thesewhatever I want.
It looks at the method signature,and it says wow!
He or she wants this andthey want that.
So I'll have to go and find out ifI know how to make one of those.
>> Right.Then typically there's some sort of
mapping in dependency injectionthat says, if you're looking for
one of these things,this interface hosting environment,
you're actually going to use oneof these concrete objects instead.
>> And before, you had mentionedconfigure services and
how configure is differentfrom configure services.
There's a lot happening inside ofsomething as innocuous as Add MVC,
isn't it?
>> Yeah,there's a lot of configuration,
a lot of services tosupport the MVC framework,
to do being configured insidethe dependency injection container
all wrapped up in thisone little method for us.
>> And in a previous example,during the beginner
ASP.NET Core 1.0, we made justa very simple directory browser.
We turned on static files and thenwe said add directory browser or
use directory browser andthen we get an error.
It blew up.
It said, I am not able to findHTTP format or something,
something while tryingto get this other thing.
>> [LAUGH]>> And basically,
I wanted a directory browser andsaid well, in order to do that,
I'm in need to be able tomake HTML and format HTML.
So, it started to build thisdependency tree, it didn't know.
And I needed to then go andadd directory browser.
And if we hover over that, it saysadds the middleware services, right?
It lets the system know aboutall of those things that I
might need later.
All right, so down here inconfigure, this is what we used in
our last little lab,i'm gonna remove all of this here.
This is the stuff that we built lasttime, this was the little bits of
middle-ware and we'll just getthat back down to it's default.
So that's->> Yeah,
that extra exception handling stuff.
>> Right.This is just what you get out of
the box when you typicallymake a file new project.
We've got ApplicationBuilder app,
HostingEnvironment which doesn'tlook like we even need right there.
We could actually build this and
see that it goes and then I couldremove that, do I have any env?
I do, I need it right there.
>> Yeah, mm-hm.
>> Say add that back all right,and again,
it's not this name that matters,it's just that interface name.
Okay, so what we'll do iswe're gonna make a piece of
middle-ware and you showed us inthe middle-ware discussion how
middle-ware canfundamentally change.
>> Yep, it can change your page,it can change your content.
>> Right, so what we're gonna dois we're gonna make a piece of
Middle-ware that's going to create,what we're gonna call, request IDs.
We're gonna make these up.
You hit it, request one, I hit it,request two and that's gonna give us
a number of things to think aboutbecause in dependency injection, at
least in ASP.NET, there's different,I wouldn't say scoping, but
there's different life cycles forobjects, how long the objects live.
>> Yeah, when I request one of theseobjects, is it the same one that's
always been around or do I get a newcopy of that object each time?
So yeah, how long dothey stick around for me?
>> Right, and the three kindsof lifetimes in the context
ASP.NET core, there's a singleton,so there's only one of these.
>> Ever, right?
>> So like IApplicationBuilder, likethere's only one and you can ask for
it as many times as you want,but that's just be one.
>> You're gettinga pointer to that object.
>> All right!
And then there's Scoped, this isthe term they use in ASP.NET Core.
Scoped, and what does that mean?
>> So Scoped says within the contextof this one request, this one HTTP
request, pass the same instanceof that concrete object around.
So at the first requestof that object,
you're getting new instance of that.
But in every subsequent request forthat object within your classes,
as long as it's within the same HTTPrequest, you'll receive the same
instance from the dependencyinjection container.
>> So let me see if I can that Ican explain it in another way and
see if I can get right.
>> Sure.
>> Lets' say I've got middle-warepipeline with a lot of different
pieces in the middleware,a single call comes in,
runs through that pipeline andwithin that,
lots of people want to use my objectlike a log object for example.
>> Sure, sure.
>> They're gonna say give methe log, give me the log,
hand me the log, they are gonnaget the same one if it was scoped.
>> Yes.>> Cause it's scoped to that
context.
>> You might also do that withI guess database connection.
>> Yep, you might havea database connection that is
a singleton depending onhow your database works.
>> Sure.It might
be one database connectionper request or a transient.
>> Right, the third option.
>> Which would be a newone every time you ask.
>> Yes, every time you ask forone, starting new copy
of a new instance of that object andsort to pass it in.
>> Okay, so let's see ifwe can look at request and
just make up a number to assign torequest and how we would do that.
So I'm gonna make a piece ofmiddle-ware right now and
I will go over into,My Solution Explorer.
We've got our Controllers folder andour Views folder.
I'm gonna make one,we'll just call it Services. Oops.
It's hard to see.
Here we go.
I tried to zoom and then Imake it so I can't see myself.
We're gonna add a new class,
so these request IDs reallyare just gonna be kind of a number.
We'll say RequestID.
And again, this something thatwe are making up, all right?
>> All right,simple example just to show that
we're counting the requests thatare coming into the service.
>> Right.
This is not, nothing morethan what we've made up.
We are gonna go and say string IDand we'll have, you can get them.
That's basically all they are.
It would probably bean IRequest id I would think.
And then->> We're
gonna want to change that toan interface from a class.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Well, I need to makean actual RequestID first.
Actually, let me back up.
There's a RequestID, right?
Or do you think I shouldmake it an interface?
>> Start with the interface.
>> Okay.
So to be an IRequestID you didthat right there, is that correct?
>> We need an interfacedeclaration on line 8.
>> Public interface IRequestID.
>> There we go.
>> All right, cool.
And then->> And
then we can implementthat interface.
>> Sure, well and then I could also,
I think I can implement thatinterface and let's go and
make a factory of things thatis gonna go and make those.
So, it's public interfaceIRequestIDFactory And this is gonna
be the thing that'll make them,it'll divvy them out, right?
Dole them out.
>> Sure.
>> Make a string, MakeRequestId.
Okay, let's see ifwe get this right.
Does that look right?
>> Looks good.
>> Okay, so
that's an IRequestIdFactory>> Uh-huh.
>> So then we'll needan actual RequestIdFactory,
derives from IRequestIdFactory.
Look at that, cool.
>> Implement it.
>> Implement that right there?
Okay, so our RequestIdFactoryis gonna be the thing
that makes them, right?
>> Uh-huh.>> It's gonna divvy them out.
So each time I ask for it,it's gotta do something.
So does it make a new GUID,a new globally unique identifier?
>> That's not really as interesting.
>> No, we need an integer, okay?
Really allows us to count and
see that this requestcame after that request.
>> Interesting, so by making aninteger, having it increase in size,
we're gonna know thatone came after that one.
So, then we'll sayprivate int requestid.
Okay, so then our MakeRequestIdwhich by default says,
hey, I'm not implemented,will have this go and return.
And then we're gonna take that ID,
this requestId here,and I could say ++.
But why would be a problem?
>> Yeah, you know what?
That's not thread safe.
If we're using a Singleton, if we'reusing one of these other models,
these scoping where wecould have multiple threads
requesting access to thisat the same time, you
could end up with collisions there->> Right.
>> Right?>> Not incrementing it properly,
not managing the integer properly,so
I think I want to do a littlemore thread safe there.
>> Okay, so what we're gonna do iswe're gonna take this integer here
and we're gonna use a thing calledInterlocked Which is inside
of the System.Threading and we'regonna say Interlocked Increment.
We're gonna go and incrementthat as an atomic operation.
>> Yep.>> Okay.
>> And I think we need tomake that a reference.
>> Uh-huh, exactly, because youdon't actually pass in a copy of that-
>> Right.
>> Integer, you pass in a referenceto it, so a pointer to that,
a reference to that.
So we're gonna increase that insize, and then pass back the string.
So our factory now, each time youcall it, you're gonna get one, two,
three.
>> Right, and to be clear theInterlocked Increment is a thread
safe way to work with that integer.
>> Uh-huh.
>> So we wont be blocking,we'll be working with it discretely.
Okay, so we've got ourIRequestID and we can go and
make a,just like we had one interface and
then implemented it,let's say RequestID.
And this one is going to have an ID,IRequestId.
>> The capital D,>> Capital D, there we go, okay.
So then where shouldit get that from?
Right, when you want a RequestId andyou say hey, RequestId.Id,
that should go and get thatfrom the RequestFactory, right?
>> Yeah.>> So this RequestId has
a constructor.
And it's gonna need to geta hold of that factory and
then take that ID anddo something with it, right?
>> Uh-huh.>> So then, it might have an ID and
pass that around.
Somehow thing's gonna startgetting a little hairy.
This is pretty simple, but you canstart to see that there's a little
bit of inter tangled->> Yeah, there's-
>> Bit of relationships there.
>> There's dependenciespassing back and
forth here that would be trickyto new up by themselves.
>> Right, so like forexample here in RequestId,
do I make a RequestIdFactory?
What we'll do is we'll try tohave it say that it needs one.
>> Yeah,>> By putting it into the method
signature of the constructor hereand then I'll scroll it away.
We see this before we sayunderscore and something.
That's kind the way to saythat this is a private,
it's kind of a standard way.
We'll say MakeRequestId which isgonna do that Interlocked Increment.
So we'll say private or we'll saya readonly string of RequestId.
Okay, so let's look at this fora second.
Here's an interface that sayshere's how we do RequestIds.
We'll hide that.
We've got a actual implementationof RequestId that's gonna take
a factory.
I'm not newing anything.
Notice, I haven't saidnew anywhere in here.
And we're just gonnascroll away that ID.
And this is a little bit verbosesaying get and all that.
I'm actually gonna doa simpler property getter with
our handlers operator orthe little hash rocket there.
>> Yeah, the C# 6 feature.
>> Uh-huh, sowhen we asked for an ID,
give them the private andinternal one, okay?
>> Yep.
So then the question is,how long do these things live, okay?
We haven't said newanywhere in here.
We haven't newed anything up.
>> No, these are classes thatstand by themselves right now.
>> Uh-huh, butRequestId needs a RequestIdFactory.
>> Uh-huh.>> So,
one of those needs to be made or
at least handed in toRequestId at some point.
And RequestIdFactory,how many of those should there be?
>> Yeah, if we're managingthe RequestIds across all requests
coming into the application,you really only want one of these.
>> Okay, so then that would imply
that a RequestIdFactorywould be a Singleton.
Okay, there's just one forthe whole app shared across the app.
>> Yep.>> All right, so then RequestIds,
when someone asks for one,how long should they be?
Because I might ask forRequestIds multiple times, but
I don't know if I necessarily wantone request to have it's ID change
within the request.
>> Yeah, you're gonna want kindof pointers back to the same HTTP
request from those various places,whether it's a Razor page, or it's
a piece of middleware, or if it's inthe middle of that MVC controller.
>> So we want that to bescoped to the current request.
>> Yeah.>> So when someone asks for
one of those, they are gonna getone whose life cycle is set by
ASP.Net Core in the dependencyinjection system and not by me.
Again, I never saidnew anywhere here.
So here's where things get cool.
Remember before we were insideof ConfigureServices and
we talked about how that's where weprepare the pipeline and let them
know about all the differentservices that are available and
then later on use them.
Let's go in here and
say services because this isgonna be a collection of service.
Like the ability to make RequestIds->> Yep.
>> Is a service now->> That is available to our
application, okay.
And we zoom in on here,and we see AddScoped,
AddSingleton and AddTransient.
>> There they are.
>> Those are the few typesthat you pointed out, right?
Okay, so what do we got here?
AddSingleton is 2 orthere's actually several.
There's 9 different ways to do this.
And you can pass in Funcs ofFunc and all kind of cool stuff.
>> Yeah.
>> I like to keep it a littlesimple because I'm not
too clever and I'll say,IRequestIdFactory.
Notice how it's not popping up.
It's because it's missingmy namespace services.
>> Uh-huh.
>> So I can click on that.
>> Getting some help fromVisual Studio there with the-
>> Yeah, I can click on
the little light bulb there, butI like to go and hit Ctrl+.+ Enter.
>> Yeah.
And that actually added it.
And I know it workedbecause it turned color.
>> Yep, that Ctrl+., is so helpful->> Yeah, it is.
>> In going through andwriting code.
>> Ctrl+., and Ctrl+,are the two things I use the most.
Ctrl+, let's me do quick navigation.
So if I'm gonna go Ctrl+, and thensay RequestId and then go right to
where the Ctrl+, ConfigureServicesand we're right back there.
A real quick way tonavigate those two.
>> Now then, when you createthat Singleton there with
the AddSingletonstatement you've defined,
here's the signature that ifsomebody requests this type you also
need to specifythe concrete type there.
>> So this is the thing I want.
When I need IRequestFactories, who'sthe one that's gonna handle it?
If we zoom in there it say's,okay, cool what's the service?
>> Uh-huh.
>> IRequestFactory the thingthat make's a request.
>> Yep.
And what is the implementation?
As you said the concrete->> Yeah.
>> Implementation of that.
Excellent, andthat's a type name, okay?
>> Mm-hm.
>> RequestIdFactory,so this says hey,
ASP.NET Core anytime anybody comesaround asking for RequestIdFactory,
this will be the onethat handles it.
>> Yep.>> And
they don't have tobe named the same.
They used to be calledSUPERFOOFACTORY it doesn't matter as
long as it is a thing thatimplements IRequestFactory,
all right.
So then, we want to say AddScoped,so RequestID's themselves.
Don't last too long, butjust the right amount.
So, those servicesare now in the same
collection of services that Mvc is.
>> Now, if we talk about the methodsignatures there on lines 34 and 35.
You're passing in type names forthose concrete implementations.
>> Right.
>> So, when the frameworkgoes to create those,
the Singleton<RequestIdFactory,it's gonna look for
a method, a constructor signaturethat it knows how to complete.
Now our RequestIdFactory,didn't have a constructor that had
parameters that it needed togo figure out how to create.
So, it knows how to new that up, so
when it goes to create thatSingleton, it'll create a new and
it will stash it with thatsignature that we're using.
>> I see, so you're saying this isa really easy class for it to make,
cuz it has itself, no dependencies.
>> No dependencies, butwhen goes to create the requestID,
the first time that it's requested,it's gonna request a new requestID.
And go figure outthose constructors,
I need an IRequest IDFactory,go resolve, get that Singleton, and
insert it in, and then passyou the fully instantiated.
>> So that implies that I need tomake sure that all of the different
services that I couldpotentially need, are added?
>> Yes.
>> And if you do a callback to many,many hours ago when Maria and
I, were doing our directory browser.
We saw where we said use directorybrowser, and then it said,
I was trying to make a directorybrowser, but I came upon this thing
downstream somewhere calledHTML formatter, I got stuck.
That needed to be inthat service collection.
And in fact, we could probablyput a breakpoint there,
and look at the collection as well,
if we want to see allthe different things in it.
>> So, quick for the viewers, thatpop-up window that you showed us
there, what's the hotkey to bring that up?
>> That is Alt+F12, so I liketo go and say, go to definition,
this is peak definition.
So I'm in this tab, andI'm looking at a RequestID, and
I'm thinking about RequestIDs,I can go and say, Peak.
>> There it is.
>> AndI get a window within a window.
And what's cool about that is thatit's real, I can look around there.
So, this is a really nice way forus to see, that RequestIds need
RequestIdFactories, andhow that chain of dependency works.
>> There you go.
>> Good observation anda good thing to point out.
All right, so that's interesting.
Those are just two POCO's,
or Plain Old CLR objects thatare out there in the world.
We don't actually have, anymiddleware to do anything with them.
>> Right, they're just livingout there, nobody is creating or
requesting them yet.
>> That's a good point.
Even though we have added itto the services collection,
it's not gonna ever be madecuz no one ever needed one.
>> No, nobody is instantiating it.
>> So let's go over here.
And these folders reallyare just convention,
it's up to you how youwanna name your folders.
But having one for services is nice,as is having one for middleware.
>> Yeah.
>> So middleware, this is gonnabe like your custom middleware.
And it's gonna sit in the pipelineand it's gonna do stuff,
it's gonna use thesedifferent services.
So I'm gonna say, Add > Class and
we'll make a RequestIdMiddleware.
In this RequestIdMiddleware,is gonna have a constructor,
that is going to be just like yours.
When we make some middleware you'regonna need to have a few things
passed in.
First there is a RequestDelegate.
That all comes out of HTTP namespace inside of ASP.NET Core.
So you need the next one.
Now, we want a new RequestId Inour middleware cuz we are doing
stuff with RequestId's, so we'regonna need that name space as well.
>> I think it's capital D andthere we go.
>> Fixed it and out of it usingat the same time, cuz I'm fancy.
>> Nice.
>> Yes.
Then, let's have a logger as well,cuz right now we have all
these things available to us, whynot have it log things, that's cool.
And we'll say, we'll needan ILogger that knows about
RequestIdMiddlewares, we'llname it logger.
So, we're able to start this classup, and we've already go whole
bunch of stuff, available to us andwe didn't have to new anything.
>> No, we didn't.
It's just gonna be passed in, andcreated as needed with the scopes
that are defined, inside thatconfigure services method.
>> Exactly.
So, because our invoke isgoing to need hang on to next,
to the next bit of middleware,we'll just take a moment and
we will squirrel awaythe next delegate.
That's gonna hang on to whatcomes next in the pipeline.
And then, we're gonna go andtake our logger and
since we got one passed in,we're gonna want to hang on to it,
so we can use it forthe life of our object.
And that is gonna beRequestIdMiddleware, and
that one was called _logger.
And what we're gonna do is,in this next is passed to and
logger is passed there it's _next= next, and _logger = logger.
I think there's ways to makethat a little cleaner, but for
now I think that will be fine.
>> Yeah.
>> Then, remember whata middleware has to have.
>> Has to have that invoke method,Scott?
>> Mm-hm, that is the onething it has to have,
it's almost an interfacewithout an interface.
>> It is.>> It's an agreement,
that they know how to be invoked,and as you pointed out
in the middleware section,I get passed in the HttpContext.
And we're gonna alsohave it get a IRequestID.
So, painful to watch someoneelse type, isn't it, Jeff?
You're being very kind.
>> I am, yeah.
>> [LAUGH]>> Somebody once said,
this is what it's likewatching your manager type.
>> That's so painful.
You know, I type a 100 wordsa minute, but 90 of it is errors.
Yeah, it's mostly backspace.
>> I IntelliSense 90 words a minute.
>> Actually, that's a good point,IntelliSense should count towards
your ultimate typing speed,but it doesn't.
>> It doesn't.
>> So, we're gonna go andsay logger,
and we talked about this duringdiagnostics and logging section.
>> Yeah, look at those log methods.
>> Exactly, and
this is gonna follow, we saw howwe can configure your logging and
say, only shown me critical, oronly shown me warnings and above.
We're gonna say,
go in the logInformation, this iskind of an informational thing.
And then we're gonna used ourfavorite thing in the world,
which is the string interpolation.
We'll say, this is Request andthen we'll say requestId,
I love getting IntelliSenseinside of a C# string.
It still seems impossible.
>> This feature has
completely changed the wayI type strings in C#.
>> Yeah, it's good.
So, there we go,request right now is executing.
This one's squigglingbecause it feels like
something is not happening.
We never->> We have returned anything.
>> [CROSSTALK] the next, exactly.
So we'll say, _next andwe'll pass our context.
So, all we're gonna doin this thing is Invoke.
But you know what I'm realizing?
Once again, we went an entireclass without newing anything.
>> Yup.
>> We simply said,we need a requestId.
And here's anotherinteresting thing.
I don't see anything abouta RequestFactory here.
>> Right.
>> Yeah, we didn't even haveto worry about that, did we?
Because the RequestIdFactory,was the thing that handled that.
So, we have a little bit ofa single responsibility principle.
>> Yup.
>> And notice also, we asked fora RequestID right here.
But we never madea RequestIdFactory,
that gets made for us.
>> Exactly.
>> So, no one that we know of, or
see, makes a RequestIdFactory orvisibly calls make RequestID.
It's all being hidden from us.
>> It's middleware forthe middlewarer.
>> We did actually some middlewareservices, for our middleware,
that's a good point.
So, there's a couple ofthings that we can do here.
We can go andadd this RequestIdMiddleware,
remember our name space thatit's in, by going into startup.
And we've got our list ofkinda existing middleware,
I think that that probablyseems like a good spot.
>> Yeah.
>> You did a thing that was cool.
You said Use, andyou had Jeffs awesome middleware or
whatever, you had a use method.
>> You coulda just stopped at useJeffs awesome, that's pretty.
>> Sure, sohere what I'm gonna do is,
I'm gonna use a more generic one soI don't write that sugar.
>> Sure.>> I would say UseMiddleware,
and then I'm gonna sayRequestIdMIddleware.
And you see,it's not able to find that.
Because it's inthe middleware namespace.
It went and fixed my spelling erroras well, which is pretty cool.
So I could go andmake a helper function.
UseRequestIdMiddleware.
>> Sure could, yeah.
>> Which is cool.
>> Yeah.>> It gives you IntelliSense and
it's friendly.
But if I don't wanna do that Idon't have to do that, I can go and
just do it like this.
But I wanna make that littlebit of sugar that you sent.
So I think that looks good.
Let's go andmake sure that we're running this.
I'm gonna do it under Kestrel,cuz I'd like to see my messages at
the At the command prompt there,the DOS box.
And we'll run this application andcheck it out.
>> Do we still call it the DOS box,or
do we now call it the shell window?
>> It's a command prompt.
I mean there's PowerShell,there's Bash,
there's, I made it green tomake it look like an Apple II.
So, you know,ultimately I can't win.
>> Reminds me of a 3270.
>> It's good,that just means that you're old.
So check this out, look.
Request 2, request 3,we can actually go in and
see how many requests get called.
>> So, why don't we try this?
>> Okay, what do you got?
>> So we put in that this isset on a scoped request, right?
>> Mm-hm.
>> Why don't weinject the request ID
into the view thatyou're showing there?
>> All right.
>> Wait, that's not a view, is it?
>> No, it is.
>> Okay, why don't youinject it into the view.
>> Why don't you showme how to do that?
>> Okay, sowhat we do is we add a new directive
there after Model, it is @Inject.
Lower case, and then space.
And then it almost follows thesyntax as though we were declaring
a variable.
So you specify the typethat you're looking for.
>> The type in thiscase was a request ID.
>> You're looking for an IRequestID.
>> And I think it was inWebApplication22.Middleware.
Is it in middleware?
>> Well, you're right.
>> It's in Services.
>> It's in Services, thank you.
It is in Services, all right.
>> And then after that, you need tospecify the name of the variable
that you're gonna be receiving.
>> Let's say just req.
>> Sure.
>> Okay.
>> So now let's output that req IDa little bit further down there.
So @req.
>> It can't be that easy.
>> Isn't there a propertyon there we need to?
>> Yep, .Id.
>> There we go.
>> But still, it can't be that easy.
>> It can't be, but it is.
>> Are you sure?
You're freaking me out now.
Let's find out.
>> It's like we planned this.
>> [LAUGH] It's almost likethere's a script, Jeff.
>> Request ID 2.
>> The irony, of course,is that there's no script.
>> Now, so you're seeing request ID.
>> Did you notice one,did you notice something funny?
Let's do that again.
People might be wondering,cuz it skipped a number.
>> It did.>> You know why?
Look, there's 2 and there's 3.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> Is it requesting, no,favicon.ico is in there.
See it requesting?
>> Where is that, show me.
>> Third line from the bottominside that, there it is.
>> Yep, see that.>> Request starting.
>> The favorite icon,
the favico, that's the littleicon that goes up there.
>> Yup.
>> That is a request.
And because, this is really,really important to remember,
because middleware is as mucha handler as is a module,
it's listening to everything.
>> Every request for every file.
>> So I would need to change that tosay, well, I only care about pages,
or I only care about images orwhatever.
It's up to us.
>> So you could change wherethat middleware is called so
that it occurs aftertransmitting those static files.
And then it won't affect,
it won't trigger when those staticfiles are being transmitted.
>> Exactly.
Right here I'm justholding down Ctrl+R.
This is my poor man's load test.
>> There you go.
>> But it's an interesting point,though, because it
does also bring up that issue ofthe original reason that we went and
did this the way we did,
is that you might very well havepeople doing stuff simultaneously.
And you need to make sure that youdon't have any threading issues.
So we did a very, very simplebit of business there to go and
say Interlocked.Increment andgo and Id++.
>> Yep.
>> On that particular item,all right.
So that is, I think, a pretty visualway to look at dependency injection.
I think the only thing thatwasn't discussed there would have
been transient.
Here's a question.
Could we, for lack of a better word,break this or
do it wrong if we changed the waywe registered these services?
>> Absolutely.
Why don't we do that real quick?
So when you addedthe RequestFactory as a singleton,
let's change thatto an AddTransient.
>> That's probablygonna break something.
AddTransient, sowhat is it transient?
It doesn't?>> So transient says every time that
one of these is requested,I'm going to create a new instance.
>> Okay, soa new instance of the factory.
>> A new instance of the factory.
>> Okay.>> So we haven't actually changed,
this is important,
we haven't actually changed theimplementation of the request ID.
We didn't change any of the requestID or request factory related code.
>> Correct, right.
But now, take a look at our log andour output HTML.
>> Look at that.
Everything is request 1.
>> Right, because each timethat it requests the factory,
it's getting a brand newinstance of the factory.
>> Interesting, okay.
So what if we change the factoryfrom transient to scoped?
So at least it wouldbe same per request.
[CROSSTALK] Butevery request would get their own.
>> Right.
[CROSSTALK] the same thing.
So if you were requesting thatmiddleware several different times
within the scope of that controller,you might see that number increment.
>> I see.So if we put it in multiple places,
in subviews and differentlocations within our application,
at least the numberwould remain the same.
>> Yep.>> But because
the factory is not a singleton,it would always be 1.
>> Yep.
>> All right.
So scoping is so important andsuch a fundamental aspect of this.
>> It is.
>> It's also worth pointing out thatwhile dependency injection is kind
of baked into ASP.NET Core,
you don't have to doanything to make it happen.
You don't have to turn anything on.
It's there by default.
>> You don't have to useit if you don't want to.
>> Exactly.
You could new thingsup all you wanted.
>> Absolutely.
>> But eventually,it'll probably hurt.
>> Yeah, it's a good developmentpractice to use this.
>> But it's important to note alsothat there are great third-party
dependency injectionsystems out there.
>> Yes.
>> You can check out Autofac,there's different injections,
so if you like this style,that's great.
But if you have a preference foranother system,
like a third party one,
like I use Autofac as an example,be sure to explore those as well.
Cuz some people like to declarethese things in different ways.
>> Absolutely.
And you pointed out that it isused throughout the framework.
Every class that the frameworkcreates is eligible to be connected
to with dependency injection, setup the constructor parameters, and
those will be passed into,as well as the views.
The views, that's really the newone that we never really had before
in older versions of ASP.NET.
Injecting things into the views,
while cool, might not beapplicable in every scenario.
It might be better topass them as models.
>> All right, so that is a generalsense of a dependency injection and
how it works on ASP.NET Core.
We'll take a short break and we'llcome back and talk about web APIs.
>> Fantastic.