Hey there.
Welcome back to ASP.NET Core1.0 Intermediate tutorials.
My name is Jeff Fritz, and this is->> Hey, I'm Rowan Miller.
I work as a program manageron the Entity Framework Team
here at Microsoft.
>> So we're going to continue goingthrough some of our content about
ASP.NET core 1.0.
And we're gonna build on some ofthe things that we did a little bit
earlier today.
So, we've done lists ofproducts through a web API.
And we've done some otherthings with data in memory.
But what happens when we needthat data to persist, right?
A database or some other storagemedium would be a great help,
but we really want to get intosaving to that database, and
we want to use a tool likeEntity Framework to help with that.
So we saw a little bit with EntityFramework in our security module
when we added Facebookaccess to the application.
Let's take a little bit ofa deeper look at Entity Framework
in this module.
So Rowan, what is Entity Framework?
>> So, Entity Framework is an objectrelational mapper for .NET.
So it's kind of two parts to that.
So, an object relational mapper is,I write objects.
I'm writing C#, orVB.NET or something.
I'm writing classes,and I wanna write code.
>> Okay.
>> I'm mapping toa relational database, and
those two thingsare not the same thing.
In one, I write C#,in the other one, I write SQL.
>> Right.>> And so,
an object relational mapjust bridges that gap.
It maps between the two.
It means I can writequeries in code, and
the object relational map will takecare of translating those into SQL.
>> Queries in C# or .NET code?
>> Exactly.
>> Okay.
>> Yep, absolutely.
And then for .NET, obviously it justmeans that this Entity framework
specific to .NET code.
>> Okay.>> So, primarily C# and VP.net.
>> Gotcha, so then, what's thedifference between entity framework,
and now I hearEntity Framework Core?
>> Yeah, so we often refer tothat as Entity Framework 6.X,
because we're currently on 6.1.3>> So,
that's how we talk aboutthat part of the stack.
>> Okay.>> Entity from a core is this kind
of newer lighter weight thing.
It fits very nicely when we thinkabout .NET Core and ASP.NET Core.
It's lightweight,
it's cross-platform, and it's kindof a re-imagination of the framework
we want to take forward forthe years to come.
It is, obviously,the new thing at the moment, too.
Entity Framework 6 is obviouslythe battle-tested, proven thing, but
of course, only runs on the full.NET framework, not these new places
like UWP and cross-platformwhere .NET Core is taking us.
>> Cool, all right.
Why don't you show usa little bit about that?
>> Yes, let's hop over to my screen.
I've got Visual Studio open here,
and I've created the start ofan ASP.NET Core application.
And I've basically just donefile new project with the new
project template.
>> Okay.>> There's a couple of things I've
changed, which I'll just walkyou through quickly now.
If we go and
look in my project JSON- Asidefrom what is installed by default,
you see I've had references toa couple of other packages here.
So I've gotEntityFrameworkCore.SqlServer here.
So this would be the SQL Serverprovider for Entity Framework Core.
We should mention thatEntity Framework works great
with SQL Server, but also works witha whole bunch of other databases.
>> Okay.>> SQLite, MySQL,
all the other main databases.
And so we are installingSQL Server Provider,
because that is what I am goingto use for this particular demo.
>> Okay.
>> And I've also installedthe Entity Framework Core tools.
>> So this allows me to use commandline tooling that is part of
Entity Framework Core.
And then you'll also notice I've gotthe SQLServer.design package here,
and this just plugs in someextra tooling that's specific to
SQL Server, which we'llsee in action in a minute.
>> Okay, andthese are updates to project JSON,
these are NuGet packages that wereinstalled either by Visual Studio,
or by running that.NET restore command.
>> Yep, so, could have right clickedon references and manage packages.
I could have handed inmy project JSON, and
I could have run commandsin Package Manager Console.
>> Okay, cool.
>> So you get packages.
Okay, now, when we demo EF,we often start with a new database.
We write some code, and then wegenerate a database from the model,
which is how somepeople get to work.
But lots of us have towrite applications against
an existing database.
>> Yeah.>> I thought today we would actually
start with an existing database.
>> Cool.>> I've got SQL Server object
explorer here in Visual Studio.
You see I have a productsdatabase here,
very simple model that we shouldall be pretty familiar with now,
has a products anda categories table.
>> They would have all of thecolumns we would expect in there and
a relationship between them, okay?
Now we want to, we could handed it,we could hand code a model here.
We could write some code toconnect to this database.
But that's gonna be prettytime consuming to do.
For a trivial database like thiswith two tables, not too bad.
But if I had something bigger,with hundreds of tables in it?
That would take a really long time.
>> And when I try to do that,
I always gets a disconnect betweenmy data types, and some of
the constraints on the data typeswhen I'm building my .NET classes.
>> Yeah, and so, you're gonna spenda lot of time debugging trivial
things that don't really help writeyour application at all, right?
So, be better to spend our timejust focusing on the finer
aspects of our model.
So we're gonna use sometooling that we had,
we saw those toolspackages I had installed.
So we're gonna use a commandcalled Scaffold-DbContext-
>> Okay.
>> Because I'm scaffoldinga DbContext from a database.
Now, I need to pass thisa connection string.
Everyone knows how towrite connection strings.
I'm just gonna copy andpaste it in there, right?
You don't want towatch me type that.
The three things I'm calling outin my connection string here are,
first up, the server.
I'm connecting to mylocal DbInstance.
The database on thatis called Products,
that's the one I just showed you.
And we're using integratedauthentication,
Windows Security, basically.
>> Okay.
>> And then the next thing I need todo is tell it what provider to use
to connect, becausethe connection string doesn't
tell me that this isa SQL Server database.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Okay, so we're gonna point it toMicrosoft.EntityFrameworkCore.SqlSe-
rverProvider.
That is the name of the NuGetpackage, basically.
That's a easy way toknow what to type there.
>> Okay.
>> So, the name of our provider isthe same as the name of the new
package you installto get the provider.
>> Okay.>> And we saw that
name in my project JSON.
>> And is that by convention, or isthat truly the NuGet package name,
because if I grab somebody else's,some third-party provider's package,
is it still that package name?
>> It's actually the assembly name->> Okay.
>> Which almost always alignswith the NuGet package.
So, yes, essentially it is,by convention, the NuGet package.
Now, because I'm inASP.NET application,
I would typically put my modelclasses in a folder called Models.
That's not always the case on alldifferent types of platforms,
but ASP.NET,that's typically what I do.
So I'm just saying the outputdirectory is Models.
>> Okay.>> I really
want this stuff inthe root of my project.
So I'll run that,it should execute pretty quick, and
then it will generate some code.
Let's swap back toSolution Explorer.
We'll see that we havethe New Models folder here, and
I'm gonna walk through the codethat I generated for us.
>> Sure.
>> There's two parts toan Entity Framework model.
There's what we callthe entity classes.
>> Mm-hm.>> And
these are the classes that we'regoing to interact with at runtime.
So we'd expect one of these foreach of our tables.
I'm gonna want to queryinstances of my product class.
And then we have a context, and
a context representsa session with a database and
allows us to connect the databasein saved data and queried data.
>> Okay.>> So let's look at the entity
classes first.
We have category now.
I don't really likethe name categories,
that doesn't make sense foran entity type, right?
It should be singular category.
>> Yeah.>> So I'm just gonna rename it.
And this is the kind of thingI want to spend time doing
like tidying up names.
It's gonna ask me if I wannarename the class as well, so
yes, I do wanna do that.
You'll see I have a propertyhere with a getter and a setter.
There's a generated,
based on the columns thatwere found in the database.
>> Okay.>> Then we also have a relationship
between the two of them.
So, a category hasa collection of products.
And this is wherethe object-relational
mapper really comes in.
Because I don't want to have tothink about foreign key constraints
and how to write a SQLabout current related data.
I just want to,if I have a category, and
I want to see the products,
I just want to accessthe products collection.
So that's where theobject-relational mapper comes in.
We'll go look at the productclasses as well.
This one has a few more properties,
cuz it had a few extracolumns in the database.
And we'll see pointingback the other way if we
have another navigationproperty here.
So when the product belongsto a single category, so
we just have one of those,you'll also see the foreign
key property listed hereas well as category ID.
So, those navigation properties,
those are actuallynothing in the database,
it's just a way to traversethe foreign key relationships.
>> Exactly,you can think of it as .NET code
based obstruction over the foreignkey constraint in the database.
>> Cool.
>> So let's rename this one too,
products does make sense,let's call it product.
And we'll just say yes when itasks us if we want to rename
the class as well.
Okay, so those are the entityclasses, let's look at the context,
cuz that one's a littlemore interesting.
Now, it's worth noting the toolingthat we used can be used on
all different types of applications,not just ASP.NET Core.
So for that reason,
it's just put the connectionstring here for us in code, but
it's added a warning saying thatthis isn't the right place for
your connection string to be.
Depending on how you'rebuilding your application,
this connection string shouldgo in your user secrets or
your environment variables oran app.config-
>> Mm-hm, mm-hm.
>> Or somewhere else,
depending on what kind ofapplication you're writing.
Now, in ASP.NET Core, things likethat belong in the settings system.
So actually gonna put it in appsettings JSON for the moment.
There is nothing sensitive in here,it doesn't have user names and
passwords in it.
If it did, I might wannalook at user secrets or
a environment variable instead.
But this one, we're just relyingon integrated authentication.
So I have a connectionstring sitting here,
we'll just give it a name,let's call it products.
And I'll just paste in thatconnection string exactly as it
generated in there.
Okay, now,the other thing that's not
very in line with how we typicallygo to ASP.NET Core applications,
we just get a bit more room onthe screen here is I'm configuring
where I'm telling what databaseto connect to and everything.
If I was using entity framework in,say, UWP application or winforms, or
something like that, it would makesense to do this inline here.
But in ASP.NET Core, all this stuffis usually done in startup.cs.
Okay, so let's, let's make thisa little bit more dependency
injection ASP.NET Core friendly.
So we're actually gonnadelete all of that.
Instead of setting up the DBcontext options here,
I'm gonna add a constructor tothe context that allows them to be
passed in externally.
And the tendency injection is gonnatake care of typing the options that
are set up in startup.
And passing them into my context.
So we'll add that constructor.
For folks that don't know that,I just used a little shortcut there.
So CTOR, tab, that's snippet.
We'll give you a constructor.
That's standard in Visual Studio.
And what I'm gonna take inhere is a DbContextOptions.
And we'll call it options.
We can actually be a littlebit more specific.
We can say this is actuallya DbContextOptions for
product context.
I don't have to do that.
This would just help if I hadmultiple different contexts in my
application.
And in fact his can be true ifI'm using ASP.NET identity.
It uses an EF context and so I mightwanna say that, specifically I want
the options for the products contextinto this one not the options for
the identity context.
>> Sure, they could livein different databases.
>> Yeah.>> Yeah.
[CROSSTALK] There are some othersettings we could set up as well.
And we don't have to doanything with those options.
Other than pass them to the baseconstructor of DB Context.
>> Cool.>> And actually
that's an important pointthat I didn't point out here.
Our products context inheritsfrom DB Context, and
this is basically what givesit all of its behavior.
>> Okay.
>> I often thinkDB Context is effectively
a session with the database.
An instance of one ofthese represents a session
with the database.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay, so there's some otherthings happening in this class, too.
When EF runs, it's goingto look at our classes and
work out how theymap to the database.
And by default it will say, if I seea property named name, I'm gonna
assume that there's a columncalled name in the database too.
>> Okay.>> But when it was reverse
engineering our model,
there were a few things that itwasn't gonna pick up by convention.
For example, we had a pricethat was of type decimal.
So if we go and look atthe price property on product,
we'll say that it's of type decimal.
>> Okay.>> By default that maps to
the SQL Server decimal type.
>> Sure.>> But in my database I've
actually used the SQL Servermoney data type.
So we see a little bitof config here saying
the property price should actuallyhave a common type of money.
>> Okay.>> And then the other thing here,
the name of my foreign keyconstraint in the database doesn't
match what EF wouldcalculate by convention.
>> Yeah.>> So there's a little bit of config
here to configure the name ofthe foreign key constraint as well.
>> Okay.
>> Okay, now we'll talk more aboutdifferent options for doing this.
One of them is to do them in linein this OnModelCreating method,
you can also do them usingannotations on your classes as well.
And a little bit later we'll lookat that, because some people don't
wanna pollute theirclasses with attributes.
Other people would prefer attributesover the complexity of writing
code like this.
>> Yeah,using some of those attributes and
putting them on the classes, alsohelps with your validation then.
>> Exactly, yeah.
And so what often people would dosomething like maximum length.
So if I had a name should havemaximum 200 characters in it.
>> Yeah, sure.
That makes sense in the classbecause that's used by ASP.NET.
It's used to dovalidation like you said.
Something like configuringthe SQL server column type, and
that's starting to makesconcern a little bit.
So a lot of people would rather keepthat out of the entity classes.
>> Sure, makes sense.
>> So you can pick whatmakes sense for you.
The last thing we have hereis DB set properties for
each type in our model.
And there's only two for us, right?
Product and category.
We'll see in a minute these are theproperties that we're gonna interact
with when we want to either changedata in the database by saving or
when we want to write a queryto fetch data from the database.
>> Okay.>> Okay.
Okay, now we have to go andwork in Startup.cs.
And there's two thingswe wanna do there.
One, we wanna do the configurationfor our context in there.
But we're also gonna wanna use ourcontext in all of our controllers
and everything, right?
>> Right.>> So
this means in the languageof dependency injection,
this would be known as a service.
>> Yep.>> Context is
a service that I want to be ableto make use of in our controllers.
So we need to setupthe context as a service.
>> Now can you talk a littlebit about what a service is in
dependency injection.
We didn't use that term when wetalked about dependency injection.
>> Okay, did you use a differentterm earlier today or
we should just?
>> We used,we talked about singletons.
>> Okay, all right.>> So I
think that's whereyou're going with this.
We also talked about the scope.
>> Mm-hmm, okay.
So when I add my context,it's typically used for
a single operation.
It's not thread safe, I shouldn'tkeep it around for a long time.
I should use it to query some dataand maybe make some changes and
then throw it away.
>> Right.>> So when we talk about scopes,
it's gonna be a scoped.
>> Right.
>> Which means I get oneof them per request.
So, if I have two request comingfrom two different people, they're
gonna have two different instancesin my context class if we use them,
so that they're isolated either way.
>> Cool.>> A service is just a component or
class orsomething that we put in DI,
that we're gonna want to make useof somewhere in our application.
Other examples would belike the login manager for
ASP.NET Identity>> Sure.
>> Something that's in this bag ofcomponents that I might want to use,
and then in my controller I cansay hey, give me the context.
I don't have to worry about creatingit or knowing what scope it is or
anything I just say,I need one of these.
>> Right.>> Dependency injection will take
care of giving me one.
>> Yeah.>> Okay.
>> It sets up all the connection foryou.
>> Yeah.
So we need a connection string, so
we're going to get thatfrom configuration.
GetConnectionStrings is justbasically a sugar method that's
going to go and look in thatconnection strings section that we
had in our appsettings.JSON.
And we call them products.
So it's just going to do a patternmatch, it's going to look for
connection strings colonproducts in our complete system.
Cool And now that we havethe connection string,
we're gonna do services, and we'regonna say we want to AddDBContext.
Again, this is justa sugar method for
helping you get the contextwith the correct spelling for
getting the option set upcorrectly and everything.
You don't have to use this,you can go ahead and
just register your options andregister your context to scope and
all those things, but this makeslife easier, so we'll use it.
We'll do the product context.
And then I have the options,or the option,
to, Set up all that stuff.
So all that stuff thatwasn't on-configuring,
now I have exactlythe same API here.
>> Okay.
>> So, the method that we usedbefore was UseSqlServer which
telling it go ahead andconnect to a SQL server data base,
using the connection string thatwe just put out of conflict, okay.
There's other option on here too.
So, after I've done UseSqlServer,
I can do things like tellingit can I say batch I see you
Yeah, we can setup logging, orwe can override the model cache, or
we can externally pass in the model,things like that.
So there's extra stuffI can do here, but
the main thing that I woulddo from your SQL Server,
is tell it whatdatabase to connect to.
>> Sure.
>> Okay, so now we have our contextinterdependency injection container.
We can use it our controllers,and we're ready to go.
>> Okay.>> Right.
Now I have made a start onthe controller, just so
we have to typea little bit less code,
because I'm sure you've shownguys how to write controllers.
>> Yeah.
>> Now, we wanna make useof our context here, so
we need to write a constructor.
We'll use the ctor, stop it again,and all I need to do to get a hold
of is say that I wantthe product context here.
And dependency injection willtake care of passing it for me.
I want somewhere to stash it.
So, I'm going to sayyou say ProductContext,
create a local field for it to livein, and I'll just stash it away, so
that we can use it in our actions.
Making sense so far?
Absolutely.
All right Index onthe products controller.
We probably want it just to displaya list of all the products in
the database, right?
>> Sure.
>> Okay, so let's write our firstbit of actual data access code.
So we're gonna sayproducts = context.
Now, this is an instantsub DB context, and
it's effectively a sessionwith the database.
Products is the DBSet of Productthat we looked at before.
And then I can say, ToList.
Simplest query I can write.
It's gonna get all of the productsout of the database and
put them in a list.
>> Okay.
>> Now we should make thisa little bit more complicated,
because ASP.NET Coreworks well with Async.
So we should actually swap anduse ToListAsync and await.
Because it's an IO operation,there's no need to tie-up this .NET
thread while I wait forthis query to execute in database,
because .NET has no work todo on SQL server processes.
So this is gonna tell itto use this thread for
something else while we do it.
And then what we're going
to do is return a viewwith the product on it.
Like so.
Okay, now.
>> Easy enough.
>> I've already written the views,
just because it would takea long time to write that.
So, let me show you whatthe index one looks like.
This is very similar to what youwould get scaffolded by default,
if you're scaffolding.
We use, we're basically goingthrough it, and doing a table.
And it's gonna display the name, andthe description, and the process,
and then some links to go andEdit, Delete, etc.
>> Right.
>> Make sense?
>> Yep,we've seen this structure earlier.
>> Great let's run it.
So when our application lights up,I'm gonna go ahead and
hit the products controller.
Of course it's gonnahit our index action.
And we'll see all the productsfrom the database displayed on
the screen here.
So these are the onesI happen to have.
You might notice there'sa bit of a unicorn them here.
We can actually thankScott Hanselman for that.
Entity framework 4.1 was dubbed byhim as the magic unicorn edition.
Unicorn has kind ofstuck around since then.
You'll see it crop upin a number of places.
Now, let's go backto our controller.
What we wrote here was a query,it's actually using something
called link,which is language integrated query.
>> Yep.>> This is a way of expressing
queries not in transact sequel,but in c shop.
And so I did the simplestthing possible here.
I took the products, which isa DB set, which DB set implements
Iqueriable, which is kind ofthe root interface of link.
>> Right.>> And I did a tool list on
it, okay.
We can do extra things on here likewe can do sorting and grouping and
basically anything I can thinkof that I wanna do with queries.
So let's look ata really simple one.
So we can do it in order by here.
And say order by name.
>> And the actual translationof this C sharp code,
right, translationcompilation of it to
SQL code that SQL Server understandsis all being done behind the scenes.
It's not something we needto execute ahead of time,
it just happens.
>> Yes, I'm going to run this again.
I already have SQL Profilerrunning in the background.
So let's run this.
Let's hit the action withthe change we made, and
then we'll look at the SQLthat it generated.
>> Okay.
>> In the background.
So we'll go to Products.
We'll notice this time that allthe products are alphabetically
sorted here.
And then if I swap to SQL Profiler,and we'll see,
this is the query that wasexecuted in the database.
Now, one thing to note here,
this looks pretty similarto what I'd write by hand.
We make a real effort inEntity Framework to try to and
keep the queries assimple as possible.
And we've actually done a lot ofwork with the transition to EF Core
to simplify the actualSQL that we generate.
>> The query syntax, nice.
>> Now, in our case it'sa pretty easy translation,
because our property names allmatch our column names, and
our type name almostmatches our table names.
So there's not a lot ofmapping to be done here.
But you also, it's pulling backall of the requested columns, and
we have our order by here that wewrote in LINQ has been translated to
an order by in SQL.
>> Sure. Sure.
And in previous versions,
I remember seeing a lot of p0 andp1 aliases for the table names.
So it's cool to see that it'ssimplified and a lot more concise,
and like you said,something that I would write.
>> Yeah, exactly.
And in all honesty, a lot ofthe times when you saw SQL that
wasn't what you would write, itactually still performed the same.
>> Certainly.
>> Like the SQL Server QueryOptimizer is pretty smart.
But even that being so, you wantto be able to look at your SQL and
understand what it's doing, right?
>> Yeah.>> So if you're seeing,
you would often see thingsselected into extent 01, and
then selected again from that, and
it just makes it really hardto work out what's going on.
>> Trying to debug that workingwith a database administrator to.
>> Yeah.>> No, not fun to do.
>> Okay, so that's simple.
We've looked at queryingback a collection.
Let's just do another one.
So we can also use LINQ toquery back a single object.
So we have a Details action herewhere I would drill into the details
of one particular product.
And what I get to do thatis the ID that I'm after.
So I'm gonna say I want the product.
Again, we're going use the contextand go into the Products DB set.
We'll write a where clause.
So this is a new LINQ operatorthat we haven't used yet.
>> Right.
>> Product, andwe wanna say where the Id equals id.
And I don't want two lists, becauseI would expect one of these to come
back from the database, right?
>> Yeah.>> So rather than two lists,
let's do single.
And we'll again returna view with prod in it.
And when I'm callingthis helper method,
I'm not sure if you'vecovered this yet, but
it's basically returning the viewassociated with this action.
>> Yep.>> And
it's passing this inas the model data.
>> Yep.
>> The product that I've returned.
Now, again,we should be async friendly, so
let's swap to SingleAsync.
And we'll put an awaitin front of this.
And then let's go ahead and run.
>> And because we're usinga where method here,
it's gonna generate a where clauselike I would see in regular SQL.
>> Andbecause I only want one result,
I wouldn't expect it to return allthe data from the database, right?
>> Right.
>> Sowe'll go to the Products tab again,
and we'll just go tothe details on one of these.
And then we'll swap to SQL Profiler.
And so let's look at a fewdifferent things here.
So one thing that might not beimmediately obvious is it's doing
a SELECT TOP(2).
But I only asked for single record.
And the reasons it's doing that isSingle is very specific, it says,
there should be one record andonly one record.
So if you find two,you need to throw.
So that's the reason we select two,
just to make sure thatthere's only one.
>> Okay.
>> If two results come back,we'll throw.
If you just want the first one,there's another LINQ operator called
first, which will justgive you the first, and
it doesn't care of there's extras.
>> Okay.
>> So the reason we're selecting toptwo here is to make sure of that.
And then you'll alsonotice the where clause.
Another very importantthing to note here,
we obviously used parameterization.
We don't just hack strings together,
because then you open yourselfup to SQL injection attacks.
So we're passing in, the id wehappened to be after was 5, and so
we're passing that in asa parameter to the query.
>> Okay.
>> All right.
We've looked at a little bit ofLINQ, but you cannot express
everything in LINQ that youmight wanna do in T-SQL right?
>> Yeah.>> So a good example of that,
I have our third action here, andthis is the last query one we're
gonna do, where I wannasearch based on a term.
Now, I could products= _context.Products.
And then I could start puttingtogether where clauses here, right.
So we might say where the namecontains, and I look for
the search term, andthen I probably wanna hack together.
There are database-specifictechnologies built to solve this
problem, so full text search wouldbe a good example in SQL Server.
>> Yeah.
Right.
>> Now I actually have,if I go over to my database,
you'll see that I havea table-valued function here.
So we'll look in Programmability >Functions > Table-valued Functions,
and you'll see how Ihave a search product,
Table-valued Function in here.
And this is making use ofwhatever database features it can
to do the most efficient andmost thorough text search for
this term on Products.
>> So I can select from the resultsof this function as though this
function is a table?
>> Yes, and we're actually gonnaget to why that's important.
So what I'm about to show would workwhether this was a stored procedure
or just a function or a table-valuedfunction or whatever, okay?
So what we're gonna do is actually,Instead of querying using LINQ,
we're gonna drop down to raw SQL.
But we're not gonna lose allthe benefits of Entity Framework.
So I'm not gonna be responsible forcreating instances of my types.
I'm not gonna be responsible for
knowing which columnmaps to which property.
EF is still gonna do all that forme,
it's just gonna let me replace myLINQ query with a raw SQL query.
>> Fantastic.
>> Okay, so let's look at that.
So let's get rid ofthis where clause.
And we're going to use a methodthat is only in EF Core,
it's not in Entity Framework 6,FromSql, which takes in a string.
And as you said, with a table-valuedfunction, I do a select star from.
And the name of itwas SearchProducts.
And then it took a single parameter,which was the search term.
Now, this looks like I'mabout to do a string.format,
cuz this would bestring.format syntax.
Which obviously wouldbe a horrible idea,
cuz that would open us upto a SQL injection attack.
Cuz if someone searches forsemicolon, delete from.
>> Those magic charactersthat do things.
>> So FromSql,after it's taken the string,
can take some extraobjects after that.
So I'm gonna pass in term.
And it will take of wrappingthose up into SQL parameters and
passing them back into the stringwhere these placeholders are.
So this doesn't meanit's gonna take this and
directly translatethe string into here,
it means it's gonna createa parameter, perhaps this, and
it's gonna put the name of thatparameter where this placeholder is.
So we are SQL injectionprotected by doing this.
>> Fantastic.
>> So we'll do ToListAsync.
Of course, I need to await that.
And same thing we've been doing sofar.
I'm just going to quicklyshow that this works.
And what we would expect is for
Entity Framework to notdo anything fancy here.
I told it what SQL to run, soI would expect it to go and
execute exactly that SQL for me.
>> Yeah, pass it right over.
>> So let's search for
shirt, cuz I know I havea few shirts in the database.
Okay, the shirts come back.
And if we go look in SQL Profiler,we'll see that the last
query to execute was exactly thatpiece of SQL that I passed in.
And we'll see there'sa parameter there.
And we'll see that my term shirt hasbeen passed in as a parameter value.
>> Cool.
>> Now, when I drop down to SQL,in the past,
I've been restricted to writingthe rest of my query in SQL.
So say I wanted this data ordered.
I would have to go over here andI would have to keep writing in SQL.
I would have to say orderby name and so forth.
Then I'm losing all the benefitof the ability of EF to translate
things into LINQ.
So now in EF Core, I can actuallydo an OrderBy product.Name.
And let's run this again, it'lljust take a second to compile and
restart.
So, interestingly, what I've donehere is I started with SQL, but
then I started composingon top of it using LINQ.
>> Right.
So you were able to extend that baseSQL statement that you wrote that
was optimized for your needs,
and might have beentrickier to write, and
you've turned it into an extended,into something pretty useful here.
>> Yeah, so now we'resorted alphabetically here.
And if we look in SQL Profiler,we'll see it took that statement
that I wrote andwrapped it a SELECT,
because it's a table-valuedfunction, it can do that.
And it's put my ORDER BY atthe end here, which is quite nice.
Now, you can't do this withevery piece of raw SQL.
For example, you can't do it whenyou select from a stored procedure,
cuz stored procedures don'tsupport this composition type
thing we're doing here.
But because it was a table-valuedfunction we can compose on top of it
using LINQ.
An easy way to remember that,basically if the fragment that you
pass in starts with SELECT, thenit's composable in SQL Server and
compiler can tell ifwe're using LINQ.
>> Yeah, I suppose if you were in astored procedure returning more than
one table,you would run into problems here.
>> Yeah, absolutely.
So this is restricted tothings that work with SELECT.
>> Okay.>> Okay, so
this was kind ofan introduction to query.
>> Very cool.>> Obviously, we've covered,
kind of, we've skimmed the surfaceof what's possible with LINQ.
You can write LINQ queriesthat take up pages in coding.
>> Ugh.>> They can get very complicated.
But we've showed youbasically how LINQ works and
how we have [INAUDIBLE].
>> Yeah.We can do our simple
reads from the database.
And some more advance queriesif we need to using the FromSql.
>> Absolutely.>> Cool.
>> Okay, sothe next thing I think we should,
we can get data out of the database,
let's look at changing the datathat's in the database.
So I've got some codecommented out here,
I'm just going to uncomment it.
And these are actions that we'regonna use to create, edit, and
delete instances from the database.
Now, I'm not gonna gosuper detailed and
run it after we implement each one.
My idea here is to introduce you tothe API surface and how you use it
with Entity Framework, and then I'llpoint you to the EF docs at the end.
And this gives a whole bunch ofdetail on exactly how these things
work and everything.
So, okay, so there's alwaystwo parts to these things.
There's when we wantto create something.
There's the first action,
which just kind of populatesthe create screen for you.
>> Yeah.>> And so in our case,
a product is related to a category.
And so one of the things it's doingis creating a select list and
giving that data to the form toallow you to have a drop down with
the category in it.
Okay.
>> Okay.
The interesting one is whenthat create comes back.
And so it's gonna say, here'san instance of the product, and
we'll see that over here.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Here is an instanceof the product.
And I want you to savethis to the database.
Now, I'm gonna keep the codein here really simple.
Obviously, as you write realapplications there's gonna be some
validation you want to do.
>> Yeah, yep, we were lookingat working with model state in
our previous module that wewere talking about Web API, so.
>> So for example,
just based on this domainthat we're in at the moment,
it probably doesn't make sense forproducts to have negative prices. But,
>> No.
>> The requirement is
just to see a lot of typed decimalsso, of course, negative prices could
be added in the form we willneed some form of validation.
>> Yeah.>> [CROSSTALK] So
we're just gonna stick with thebasics of how do I save this data.
>> Okay.
>> So I would say, context.products.
Products being the DB setwhich we have used to query.
But instead of querying this time,we're gonna say add.
And we're going to pass inthat instance of the product
which MVC has handedback to us to save.
>> Okay.
>> Now, one thing of note here isthat context, when we do this,
it doesn't immediately go andput it in the database.
DB context is often referredto as a unit of work.
It kind of saves things up andit gets ready, and
then you tell it when to persistthose changes to the database.
In basic NBC actions, it's typicallyonly one thing you're doing.
You're creating one thing oryou're deleting one thing.
But as you write a more advancedapplication, you might be inserting
three or four entities as partof creating a new product.
>> Right.>> Maybe you need to create
a product details with a photo onit and some audit entry records and
things like that as well.
>> Then you need those all intothe database at the same time or
very close together.
>> Yeah, and so what we ever do,we actually batch all those up into
a single command andsend that to the database.
So if you insert four objects,
we'd insert four objects aspart of the same command.
And more importantly,we do it transactionally.
So that whole save changes isalways wrapped in the transaction.
So you don't have to do anythingwith transactions unless you're
doing something complicated EFwhen you call save changes,
which is what we're gonna call now.
And that's async, so we'll await it.
Think of this as flash allchanges to the database and
it does it automically.
So if it inserts two things and
then one fails, the wholetransaction gets rolled back.
In our case it's only one thingwe're inserting anyway so.
>> Yeah it shouldn't be too risky.
[LAUGH]>> Okay, so
that's how we add a product.
Let's scroll downa little bit further.
So we're gonna do edit next.
Again, this first action is the onethat populates the edit screen, so
it gets the data up in the form forthe user to edit.
And sothis query looks very familiar.
We're doing single async and
we're fetching back the singleobject with the ID.
One thing want I want to justcall out here, there's actually
an overload of single async whichallows you to pass in, effectively,
a where clause.
So where as we didour products.ware and
m.id = id single asyncwithout anything in it.
You can actually collapsethose down into one column.
Which is why this looksa little different.
>> Okay.
The one that we're particularlyinterested in is the edit when
it comes back.
And so in this case, it's giving usthe ID and it's giving us the actual
product that needs to besaved back to the database.
Now, there are lots ofdifferent ways to implement
the body of an edit method.
I'm gonna do the simplest one and
then I'll talk about theshortcomings of that in a second.
So we'll go to the context,we would say products and
we would say Update(product) andthen of course, we're going to flash
that out to the database so we wouldaway on context.SaveChangesAsync.
All right so, update is very simpleand it adjust literally, sends
an update statement and sets everyproperty to be the incoming values.
>> Now how does it knowwhich product to update?
>> Because of the IDbased on the products.
>> Gotcha.
>> Soby coming back has an ID on it,
they will send in an update set allof the columns to the values out of
the properties where the ID isequal to the ID of the product.
Now there are some cases whereyou might wanna do that.
One, if you have auditing orsomething the database,
you're updating a lot of columnyou might just be setting them to
the same value.
Okay, soyou can see that some people,
if all the user changeson the form is the name,
he might wanna simpler SQL statementthat just updates the name column.
>> Okay.>> So in that case what you could do
is you would query back fromthe incidence of the database and
then you would->> And then set the value.
>> Copy the values over the top.
Another place you mightnot want to do it is if
You don't have all of the propertiesof the product on the form.
In which case, you can't just updatethem all because some of them
are gonna be null and you don'twant to set nulls in the database.
>> Okay.>> And then also if I'm doing
concurrency detection where,I'm saying, if another user's edited
the record, don't just dumpyour changes over the top.
Check with the user to make sure
that that's actuallywhat they wanna do.
Yeah, we used to->> So if I'm
changing a person's name but
someone else has changed theSocial Security number, you should
probably double-check whether that'sa right edit before saving it.
>> Yeah.>> Yeah, so
this is a very naive approach, it'ssimple, it gets you off the ground.
You can write much more complicatedcodes to achieve more complicated
outcomes.
All right Delete, again it's twoactions that work together so
first one just gets a product fromthe database and displays it and
says are you sure that this isthe one you want to delete?
And then in our Delete Confirm we'resaying yes, I want to go ahead and
delete this product with this ID.
So we don't get the whole productthis time, we just get the ID.
So actually, again, there'svarious ways to implement this.
The easiest one is to go ahead and
fetch that productfrom the database.
And then once we have it,we're gonna say Products.Remove that
product that we justfetched based on the ID.
And then as we're familiar nowwe would await on our call to
SaveChangesAsync.
Makes sense.>> Makes sense.
>> Yeah.>> Let's just test out
one of these actions to make surethat we did everything right.
>> It's interestingthat the create and
the edit>> Right.
>> They're synchronously operatinglocally but it's when they flush,
when they persist those changes,that's when goes async.
>> Yeah, so when they're doingthings like adding to the context,
that is completely in memory.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So the .NET thread has workto do the whole time that that
is executing.
The place where the .NET threaddoesn't have anything to do
is when we flush themto the database,
it goes through SQL Client, Andthen it drops out of .NET and
goes down and across the networkto the server and back again.
And there's nothing for.NET to do in that period.
And so that thread can go serviceanother request while that happens.
>> Okay.>> Let's just delete one
of these products.
So let's delete the Unicorn Pencil.
It's not been a very good seller.
So we got the query from thedatabase, the confirmation screen,
we'll delete it.
And then if we go look atSQL profile we should see a,
Delete statement issuedto the database.
>> Cool.
>> We say it's paramaterized againon the Id properties, effectively,
is what we're being based on.
That all make sense?
>> Yeah, and it even selects rowcount at the end just to make sure
that it got that one row changed.
>> Yeah, absolutely,
we always check that when weissue anything to the database.
It created an insert or delete,we always make sure that the right
amount of data gotupdated in the database.
If it didn't we roll a transactionback and we let the user know with
an exception or the developerknow with an exception that.
We would call thata concurrency violation,
so you tried to delete a row butit didn't change
anything which probably isn't whatyou expected, so here's an exception
with all the details ofwhat you were trying to do.
We'll roll the transaction back andleave the database alone.
And you can write code to decidewhat to do when that happens.
>> Cool, all right.
>> Any questions onthis before we move on?
So the next thing that I wantedto show you quickly was,
we looked at creating a modelfrom an existing database.
Right.
>> Now,what if I don't wanna work it?
What if I wanna start and code and
then have a database create it forme?.
And then what if I wannachange that code and
bring the database up to datewith those changes in code.
>> Yeah.All right,
this is what we saw with migrationwhen we did things with identity.
>> Yeah, absolutely.
>> In an earlier module.
>> Okay.
So let's just close allour windows down here.
And I get things a littlemore squared away.
So in that situation,
we would have a model written incode that we would write by hand,
and we wouldn't have a database.
So, we're actually gonna stayworking in the same application.
I'm just gonna literally deletethis products database from my
local DB instance.
Will take a minute I
think I had an open connection therewhen I was looking at data from it.
And, we would at this point,
we would've written allthese things by hand.
So I would write my entity classes,
to represent the domain modelthat I want for my application.
I would have written a contextthat would have had DB sets for
all the types of the model.
>> Sure.>> Cuz ips.net core,
I would have taken myoptions externally so
it's the same as all the codethat was generated for us.
And then, I could havedone optional config here.
Now, interestingly in this case,
I don't really care what EF picksas the name for this constraint.
So I'm actually even justgonna delete this just to keep
things simple.
Don't have to, butI don't mind what that's called.
So it's less code forme to deal with.
So this is something that Imight have written by hand.
Okay now I want a database from it.
>> Okay,>> To do that we used something
called migrations.
So I add migration, it's a command,We'll call this one InitialSchema,
the name is not important Ican call this wherever I want,
call it my first migration.
All it's gonna do is it's going tolook at what has change in the model
Since the last migrationwas generated.
Now there aren't any previous migrations,
>> Right.
>> Soeverything changed in the model.
So our first migrationthat gets scaffolded,
we'll talk about exactly whata migration is in a minute, is some
statements that are telling it to goand do these things in the database.
Now this is very databasespecific at this point.
We're not talking about entityclasses and properties.
We're talking about tables andcolumns.
And we're talking about valuegeneration strategies being
the identity column in SQL.
>> And this is essentially the DDL,right.
That data definition language thatwe would use directly against
the database but it's being wrap upinto something that's .NET Friendly.
>> Exactly, yep.
Now Migrations,
the brief description Migrationis a well order set of steps,
to take a database from any versionup, to the current version.
>> Okay.
>> My database doesn'texist at the moment.
>> Yeah.
>> Now I have one Migration.
So, there's one step toget from no database to.
>> A database.
>> Current model, which would be tocreate the database and run the code
that's in here to do all the stuffcreating the two tables for me.
So, let's do that.
The way I do that iswith Update-Database.
And given that I think you lookedbriefly at migrations in identity
I'm gonna take a little more time totalk about how migrations works cuz
that's an important thingto have in your mind.
>> Please yes.
>> We say the database error but>> Per page.
Database exception page whereit gave us that cool button to
click and apply the migrations butwe didn't go through and
do this on the command line.
We kind of got the helpthrough the user interface,
through the web browser And
I don't want my QA folks or,gosh, even my users in production
to have to click that button inorder to update my database.
>> In fact, they shouldn't,
that piece of middlewareshould only be used locally.
It's more designed as an educationthing, what I'm developing.
I think once people get used to thaterror page, they should probably
proactively do that stuff inVisual Studio before they run.
>> Sure, sure, but I could seealso in a team scenario where
You're working on one set of code,I'm working on another set of code,
when we both get upto date the next day
there's some changes that you made>> Exactly.
>> I can push that button>> Yeah.
>> Without running through anythingand my stuff's up to date.
Yeah, absolutely.
Okay, so the way this worked.
It look at the migrationsin my compiled application.
>> Yep.>> So, the first
thing it did was compilethe application.
And then looked at my assemblies andall and
there's one migration in there.
This one called,let's go back over, so
the migration we'll talk aboutthe modal snap shot in a second.
So, we'll talk aboutsnap shot in a minute.
The initial schema,as long as one migration said,
this hasn't been appliedto the database.
In fact,there isn't even a database.
So, created the database andapplied this migration.
>> So, when you,When you added the migration there
in the PowerShell window inthe package manager console.
It created a class it didn't writeSQL statement it created another
class that defined,here's what needs to be applied.
>> Yap.So, in the same way that writing
into different link queries andthings like that is an obstruction
over Writing select statements andinsert, update, delete statements.
Migration is an abstractionover writing create table and
create foreign key.
>> Those DDL statements, yeah.
Okay.
>> So, it's a bridge.
It's kind of part way betweenyour model and the database.
It's written in termsof database objects but
it's still in C# anda little bit abstracted.
>> Right, right, okay.
>> The other important pointtoo is Because it's not SQL,
different providers cantranslate it differently.
So, I can run the same migrationon SQL Server and SQL Lite,
and they might generateslightly different DDL.
Cuz SQL Lite doesn't haveidentity columns in it.
>> Right.>> Okay, so we'll refresh this,
we now have the productsdatabase back.
It looks a littledifferent this time though.
It has out products in categorytables, that's what we'd expect.
But it has this new table,EFMigrationsHistory, so
let's open that.
This is how EF tells what'sbeen applied to the database.
So, remember I said it'sa well ordered set of steps?
It needs to know which stepsit needs to go through.
And so the way it knows whichones have already been taken on
the database is bylooking in this table.
So, now recorded.>> It just stores a copy.
>> This migration has been applied.
>> Nice.
>> To really get the gistof how migrations work,
we need to look at making a change.
So, I've been coding awayon my app for a while and
I realized that I really want arating property on my product, okay?
>> Social interactions.
>> Yes, absolutely, okay, So,at this point my model and
my database are out of sync.
There's no ratingcolumn in the database.
So, I'm gonna use immigration.
>> So, I'm gonna ask the question.
>> Go for it.
>> So what if they're out of sync?
That's where we start to seethat white screen error, right?
>> Mm-hm.>> Okay.
>> So, if I tried to selectproducts, it would try to select
the rating for the product and itwould generate invalid cycle because
it would try to selectfrom the rating column.
And there wouldn't be one, soI would see a SQL exception.
>> Okay.>> And, to your point,
if you have the database separationname it would be smart and tell you
this is probably because your modeland your database are out of sync.
You should scaffold a new migration.
>> Okay.
It never generates a select star,because it is
generating the select statementwith each of the properties listed.
>> Yep.>> Because you added the property
on C# side.
It doesn't exist SQLServer side soit has that disconnect.
>> Helps us know ahead of time thatall those columns need to be present
in this statement.
>> So, do you have that same problemif you add a field to SQLServer and
you don't have it in C#?
>> Depends what you're trying to do.
>> Okay.>> So, In terms of select, no.
Because to your point,we don't do a select star.
We only select the columnswe care about and
it's perfectly valid to havecolumns in your database.
That you don't care aboutin your application.
>> Okay.
>> So, maybe you have a particularcolumn that the DBI keeps
up-to-date, or a column that'smaintained by a completely separate application
>> Sure.
>> That isn't related tothe line you are working on.
>> Not in my context.
>> Yeah, so for a select it's notgonna matter because we'll just skip
that column from the statement. Yep.
>> For an insert,
it's not gonna matter as longas the database is set up to
allow either null or it hasa default value on that column.
So, it's not gonna matter if wemiss it from instant statement.
>> Got you, that makes sense, okay.
>> So, that is perfectly valid.
>> Cool.
>> Again,I can call this whatever I want.
I'm gonna call it ProductRatings cuzthat will help me remember what this
guy did Now what it's doingat the moment is working out
what changed since Igenerated the last migration.
This is where that snapshot filethat I pointed to comes into play.
So, this snapshot, over here, andsolution explorer is a snapshot of
what the model looked like whenthe last migration was generated.
And the way EF works out what'schanged is it runs your code and
gets your current model.
It runs this product snapshot codeto get the previous model and
then it does it different forthe two of them.
And in this case, it's gonna
work out that there wasa ratings property added.
Which should result in a ratingscolumn being added in the database.
>> So, at some point thatsnapshot will be updated.
>> Yeah, this snapshot now hasthe ratings Property in it.
>> Okay, so
if we're going to look through itwe found the products one, we'd say
there's a Property [CROSSTALK]>> There's a rating?
>> Yeah.
Now this is very weakly typedbecause I might later on in
the future delete thatratings property.
And so this code doesn'treference your model at all.
It's kind of weakly-ish typed.
So, it doesn't matter what happensNow migrations are the code,
they're not, don't thinkof them as designer code.
>> No.
>> These are not, you can touchthese things, we don't know get it
right, this is our estimate of whatneeds to happen in the database.
Now for simple operationslike adding a column,
it's gonna be right but I mightwanna it like default value for
the existing data in the database.
Rating of zero doesn'tnecessarily make sense for
all the existing products.
I might say all our existingproducts should get a default value
of three.
>> So, I can enter this code.
I might want to reorder operation.
I might know why in my generateddrop and create a new column, but I
actually know that that data shouldbe copied across before we drop so
I can write extra stuff in here.
It's got a package managerconsole we'll run the update.
>> Update database again.
>> Database command.
Now what it's doing it's looking atall of the migrations in my solution
or in my compiled application.
There's two of them now.
It's looking in the migrationhistory table in the database.
It only has one recordthat is applied to it,
now it knows that it needsto apply my product ratings.
>> It did the diff between the two,to see here's the one's that I need
to apply, and then there's an orderthat they need to be applied.
>> Yep, absolutely.
So, this is a date andtime stamp at the start of them,
and this defines the order.
>> Cool, they're applied in.
>> Okay, now in both of my casesthere's only been one pending
migration but of course Imight be a developer that
pulls this applicationfrom source control.
And I run update database andI don't have a database yet
in which case it will createthe database and it will apply our
first migration, then our secondmigration and now I'm up to date.
Cool.
>> Okay.And just to show that it work.
If we go and look in the migrationhistory table.Review
the data on that.
>> To records.
>> To records.That's what would we expect.
And if i look at the products table.
I will now see the new rating.
>> The rating, cool.
>> I'll introduce that.
Okay, any questions onhow migrations work?
>> No, no, you've answered them verywell as we've been going along.
>> Okay, great.
The last thing I wanted toleave you with, obviously this
has been a skim acrossthe surface of what EF can do.
>> Sure.
>> So, I just wanted toclose by linking to our docs
>> Lets close down this and
go back into edge,now the site im going to is
docs.efproject.net this willlink to our documentation for
Entity Framework Core OK, and you'llsee the things I've organized,
we have getting started for each ofthe different types of platforms, so
were looking at getting started forasp.netcore Then this would give
a walk through very similarto what we just did now.
>> Right.Okay.
>> And then the sections are reallyorganized into the same way that we
had our module organize today.
So, there's a sectionon creating a model and
I talked about how you do things,one of the things that we looked at,
we we're looking at renamingrelationships we had or
specifying data types So we had datatypes here that was example we did.
We mapped to the money data type so
you'll see here as an exampleof mapping to Varchar 200.
>> Sure.>> Okay so
how that you would find all thatstuff if I'm creating a model and
then there is querying data andsaving data,
which were the two topics which and
that covers the vast majorityof operations [CROSSTALK] Cool.
>> All right soI think that's a good introduction,
obviously there's a lot more.
But folks can go off and learn that,browse through our docs and yeah,
get up and running with data access.
>> That's a great intro andthat gets you 80 to 90% there for
most of the stuff that you need.
So, thank's so much for joining us.
That's what we're gonna talk about,it's all we've got for
the entity frameworkmodule here today.
Come on back in a little bit,we're gonna talk about publishing.
Our applications in the nextmodule of the ASP Net Core 1.0
Virtual Academy.