Hi, I'm Scott Hanselman.
>> Hey, I'm Jeff Fritz.
>> And this is, the intermediateASP.NET Core 1.0 MVA.
If you haven't seen it already,be sure to check out our beginner,
Virtual Academy that we did.
We got a whole day ofgreat content there,
to get you started at the 101 level.
And I would say, this is moreof a 201, wouldn't you say?
>> Yeah.Okay.
>> Let's get somedeeper things here.
>> So let's do this.
Let's start with a littlediscussion, about where we left off
and we're looking at this littlebasic Movies application.
It's not really complicated.
But this particular segment,is gonna focus on Tag Helpers,
which we've briefly touched on,but didn't really dig into.
>> Okay.
>> So let's fire this up andwe'll take a look,
at our fantasticallysophisticated Movies database.
This was actuallyjust auto generated.
We went add controller andwe did a little bit of crud, and
we ended up with somepretty basic stuff.
>> Crud.
You mean create, read,update, delete, right?
>> Exactly.So when you say crud,
it's like, I got some stuff andI need to do the basics.
So speaking of crud,
if we look over here on the side,we've got Delete and then Details.
It's kind of the extra D, in crud.
How does this get generated, though.
We know that there isa four loop in there,
so let's go andjust explore that for a moment.
If we go andlook at the Movies controller,
briefly We can see our GET.
So there's out GET on Index.
So you hit, /Movie/Index.
You end up here.
We grab the Movies, we put them ina list and then list of Movies,
gets sent back over to the view,alright?
>> Yes.
So then,let's look at our list here.
We have an IEnumerable of Movie.
And we mentioned before, that thisis a forward only way of going
through Movies, it's on a list.
>> You can go forward, butyou can't go backwards.
What's going on here, Jeff?
>> This purple bold text,these are Tag Helpers.
So, it's an anchor tag.
It's an HTML anchor tag, butwe've added a little extra to it,
to make it C# aware.
It's gonna have some codethat execute server side,
that'll generate andadd on some features to that.
So in this case.We have this asp-action attribute,
that we've added onto the anchor tag.
Now, we're adding a feature to it tosay, let's create an anchor tag for
the Create action, that's definedinside my asp controller.
>> Couldn't I just go New,
and that's pretty much just fine.
Like, why do I not just do that.
>> You know what, that you right.
That works right now.
In the future,if you move things around.
If you rename some of those things,you're gonna lose track of them.
By using the action attribute here,we're using routing.
And we're getting this ability tomap and recreate that route, based
on how our URL scheme, has beendefined inside of our application.
>> That's an important reminder,that routing it's two-way.
>> Yes.
>> Right, sothe idea being that if /movies/index
comes in as the URL, we figure outthat it's the, Movies controller.
But we can also say, given anyfunction on a Movies controller,
what will the URL look like.
Does that mean, I couldtheoretically change this to films.
And I will do it in one place,instead of changing it anywhere?
>> Exactly, so now that givesus that two-way capability,
if we change that inour configuration.
>> Everywhere that uses routing,
will automatically be updated forus.
>> Why is this purple andthis is not purple,
in my Visual Studio editor?
>> Right, so this is that visualcue that we're being given,
to show that there's some C# code.
There's some Server side code,that's gonna execute,
to reformat this tag a little bitfor us and do some extra work.
>> Now, the HTML Editor inVisual Studio as I start typing,
gives me all of thesebits of intelligence for
things that are built in to html.
>> And a number of them,have this dot dot dot.
So for example, forAccessibility like aria.
>> I say ..., andthen it opens up a second level.
>> Mm-hm.>> I see the same thing for asp-.
So it knows, that's not HTML though.
>> No, these are the Tag Helpersthat are available to us,
on the anchor.
These are properties,that we can start to light up
to add additional features, to howthat anchor tag is going to behave.
>> Okay.
So it looks to me like,then if I say asp-action.
So look at that, it's purple.
>> So it's Tag Helper?
Not a Tag Helper.
>> Right.
>> And then we go like this.
>> And put in Create.
That is an action on the controller,
that this current viewhas been rendered by.
>> Right.By default,
it's the controllerthat presents this.
>> That presents this, okay.
So, let's look at this andthen do a Ctrl+F5 and,
let's look at the source andsee the difference.
So we're gonna bring this up.
Where is our p?
There we go.
So here, we see asp-action,that's a Tag Helper.
It rendered that way.
Now, people who might have a littlebit of historical context,
might hear servers like rendering,and they might think web forms.
And they might think, life cyclesand controls and thing like that,
but this is a control.
And, remember how we mentioned,that the movies are forward only?
>> Yes.>> Tag helpers are forward only,
also in the sense ofyou're rendering the HTML.
And you don't get a chance to goback and render a visual tree, and
stuff like you did with web forms.
>> Right, you're only acting withinthe scope of the beginning of that
A tag.
To the ending of that A tag.
>> And anything that's hanging.
>> Anything in between,you can push a little bit into.
>> But this Tag Helper couldn'tbe written, that it could go and
manipulate this table, or dosomething in the bottom of the page.
>> That you've already lost scope,and
it's already been renderedto the output HTML.
>> Now in ASP.net NVC in the past,
I would see peopledo things like this.
And we would say, Movies.
My little smart quotes,kinda went all messed up there.
And create or whatever,and you would go and
create this action link,and it was a little weird.
What's wrong with this,what's wrong with that?
I mean, it worked before,it didn't quite look like this.
But why is,Tag Helper superior over this?
>> And the HTML helpers, they'renice, they're still there and
they can still work.
>> I'm still using them here,there's very good uses for them.
>> Absolutely.
But, it gets us out ofthat HTML editing mindset.
We're not writing tags any more.
We've flipped context,we're now writing C#.
And if we need to reach into some of those things,
that are HTML centric, you now needto generate text, inside of your C#.
To go and place thoseitems inside of your tags.
So, we lose all of this greatfunctionality that's built in to
Visual Studio, so that we can go andcreate C# strings,
inside of that actionlink method instead.
>> Another way to think about it, isthat we would be riding some HTML,
and we'd thinkingabout things in HTML.
And then suddenly,we're in this weird grey world,
where we're writing some C#.
And the context switch,is very disruptive.
>> It is, it is very disruptiveto context switch, back and
forth the C#.
And think about if you're doingthat, in the middle of JavaScript.
Now you're flip-flopping betweenHTML, JavaScript and C#.
That's a real nightmare.
So we've simplified things, sohopefully you're only context
switching, between HTML andJavaScript again.
>> Yeah, exactly.
So, this additionally, we've gota string here with a magic string.
>> Yes.
>> Right.So,
there's nothing here that allow'sVisual Studio or the editor,
to see into that.
So by accidentally, misspelled that.
It's still gonna compile, just fine.
There's no problem with that.
And i'm not gonna know that,that link doesn't work.
Until I click on it.
It'll even render correctly.
>> Yeah,it'll render just fine, but.
>> And that is a problem.
So, that is an exampleof one Tag Helper.
In fact,there's a whole series of them.
And they get added in,with this command, addTagHelper.
And we saw before, we can say,@model, and then have Movies.
That usually goes atthe top of the view.
But if I look for addTagHelperat the top of this view,
I see the @model.
I do not see, the Tag Helper adding.
How does it know aboutthis Tag Helper?
>> So, previously when we weredoing things in IIS and we had
that Web.config, that was ableto drive configuration settings,
down into our pages andto our views.
We can stash things over there andit would just be,
inherited by our views.
So instead now, we use thisview imports cshtml page,
that you can find at the rootof your views folder.
And everything that's listedinside that _ViewImports.cshtml
gets applied to the top ofevery one of our CSHTML sheets.
>> Okay.
So this is interesting.
It's got a bunch of usingstatements as well.
So I can probably simplify my modelthere and because I have using.
I have scope.
>> Yep.
>> Here we're saying,
add all of the Tag Helpersthat are in this assembly.
And this assembly comeswith ASP.NET Core.
This is somethingthat ships with it.
And we can go anddig around in here, and
find out how that got brought in.
It got brought in as a part of MVC.
And of course,the source is all open source.
We can go up to GitHub andlook at that code.
But here's what you get, right?
You get Tag Helpers forForms and Inputs and Links.
This one's really cool, Cache.
And I think Environmentis really fun.
>> Yeah, a lot of those otherones look like normal HTML tags.
Anchor is kind of spelled out alittle bit cuz it's kind of weird to
have tags [CROSSTALK] A>> Anchor is A.
>> So yeah.
>> But that's a really good point.
So let's think about that.
Let's sort this.
That's HTML.
That's not HTML.
>> Yep.>> So
Tag Helpers don't necessarily haveto augment an existing HTML tag.
>> Right,you can create your own tags.
And provide behavior forthose things.
>> And that also bringsup an interesting point.
If we look here to, this is really
overriding a tag almost and addingan attribute to the tag, right?
>> Right.>> Right.
>> We're enhancing it.
>> I go like that.
>> Exactly, we're enhancing the tag.
See how I,
now it's not a tag helper.Now it is.
But I know for a fact that thereisn't a such thing called cache.
>> No.
>> As a tag in HTML.
>> I know they added a lot to HTML5, but they didn't add cache.
>> They did not add cache.
So let's do this.
Let's run this again.
And because it's Razor,we can make it change and refresh.
Make it change and refresh.
So let's go in here,we'll go to /movies.
And I'm just gonna put that here,and I'll put that there, all right?
And this is how I typically work.
I think you're probably the same?>> Sure.
I'm very sure, yep.>> I wanna make sure that I'm
really there.
So I'll go and hit refresh.
Now I've proven that thatRazor is in fact that.
So I'm just editingthe index.cshtml view.
We're in the movies view here.
And we can go andadd something to that.
All right?
So, the cache,as soon as we hit that.
Look at that.
There's also distributed cache.
>> Ooh.>> Yeah.
So if I was gonna dosomething in a web farm and
I wanna make sure I canplug this into Redis.
>> Yeah.>> For
a more advanced cast that spansmultiple machines in a web farm.
>> Sure.
>> Okay.
So cache pops up.
What does cache haveavailable to me?
Enabled, expires, priority andthen a vary, vary by.
This feels like ASP.NET of old.
>> Yeah, this looks like the sametypes of cache vary by headers that
we had on our page directiveinside of web forms.
And it's built very muchwith the same types of
output cache management.
>> Right.
The idea being that I wantthis to be cached and
I want it to vary by, for example,a header like the user's language.
>> Sure.>> So if I'm gonna go and
cache someone in like a date timeand the first person who shows up to
my site happens to speak French,I could
cache the French long date time andthen deliver it to everyone else.
If I wasn't varying the cacheby a particular switch.
>> And then everybody getsthe French look and feel.
The French culture.
Even though you might bein the United States.
>> Exactly.
So let's take a look atan example for cache.
Here is, I'm gonna move this over.
We're gonna say this cacheexpires in 30 seconds.
Maybe I'll make it 10 seconds, okay?
DateTime.Now.ToLocalTime, okay?
So this tag,is that going to render?
Am I gonna see that in my HTML?
>> So this is interesting.
You're not actually gonnasee a tag rendered, right?
>> Mm-Hm.>> But you're gonna have this block
that's gonna end up beingmanaged by the server.
And the contents of what's insidethat block will be rendered.
>> Now, I could probably writesome code though, couldn't I.
I could say, if andthen go into the cache.
Into cache, check for something.
I could write C# code thatdid all of this, couldn't I?
>> You absolutely can do that if youneed that fine grain control, right?
But if you want tostay HTML focused,
if this suits your needs andit's very flexible.
You have all the sourcecode available to you.
So you could even extendit if you need it to.
And just use that cache and
it'll solve probably 90%of your caching needs.
>> Mm-hm.
I'm actually gonna show you,Tag Helpers and ASP.NET and GitHub.
We can actually go up there andwe can explore the code.
Remember that thisis all open source.
So I can go and find, look at that.
I've just gone right up thereto see the source code for it.
And here's the->> There's the cache.
>> Cache Tag Helper, okay?
And we won't get to deep into that.
But you can see using thatit is using a MemoryCache.
It's being held in memory.
And this actuallybuilds on top of a base
Tag Helper base thatdoes some helpful things.
There is your attributes.
>> Yep.>> We'll learn how to make our own
in a few minutes.
See each of those HTML attributesthere, when we make one in a moment,
we will see.
But where does it render?
Where does it render? Process?
>> Yes, process.
>> Yep, looking at the content.
Doing some caching.
There's all the code.
This is the code I would haveto write if I were to do
caching correctly.
And then there'syour write out that-
>> Right at the var.
>> That center content there.
>> Yep.
>> So let's try that.
Let's hit that.
And hit refresh.
So right there,it says it's 10:00 AM.
I'm hitting refresh over andover again.
That's not updating.
>> Nope it's 10:11 now.
>> There it is and there's, so
that is expiring like we said afterten seconds That's a great example.
But, could I nest them?
Could I have Tag Helperswithin Tag Helpers?
>> Yes, you can do that.
It starts to get a little tricky
with how the Tag Helpers interactwith each other, if you do have
further more complicated ones thatsome folks might be creating.
But certainly withinthat cache Tag Helper,
it makes sense to cache thingslike your anchor tag creation.
>> Right, sohere's an interesting idea.
Remember in the first video,we talk about environments and
the importance of environments.
And in the past in ASP.NET,that hasn't been built in.
>> No.>> The idea that there's develop and
there's staging and there'stesting and there's whatever.
>> Absolutely.
Make your own.
>> Right.Maria and
I had, not just production, but alsofancy production, which is better.
>> Better production.
>> Okay.
>> There happens to bean environment cache variable.
>> Yes.
>> Or cache tag.
Excuse me, an environmentTag Helper, pardon me.
So, could I, theoretically,go around this and say,
<environment names= "Production".
See how that immediatelyturned color there.
Look and then when I pasted it.
You see, that was cool.
>> Indented, yeah.
>> Need a little freeindentation there.
That's nice.
So now I've got show this whenthe environment is production and
then do this cache anddo that work there.
>> Now what if I wantedalso do that caching
if the environment was stagingas well as production?
>> So names, if I hover over it,because this is a takeover,
this is really important.
See how I hover over the HTML andit just says, yeah,
that's an h2 doesn'treally tell me a lot.
This is C# behind it right there.
So it's not only tellingme the Tag Helper, but
it's literally saying the exactobject, the exact namespace and
it says a comma-separatedlist of environment names.
>> Cool.>> So, Staging, right?
So the docs are right there as well.
>> Too easy.
>> It is too easy.
So look at that.
So we're not in production.
>> Yup.>> We don't see it.
Change it to development.
Hit refresh.
>> And there it is.
>> And we do.
Pretty nice.
So, for folks that are thinkingabout things in the context of HTML,
this just works.
It's really, really clean andit's really easy.
That's one example.
Here's a little bit more complicatedone, where we're saying not just
an action, but we're passingin additional information.
So we're saying asp-route-id.
This is additional parameters forthe route.
And then we say, edit.
So what's going on here?
Let's look at this page.
We got our list of movies, right?
Now, I wanna just make thisa little smaller and zoom in.
And what we are gonna do is,
I'm gonna hover over these butwe're gonna watch the left side.
So, watch over here on the left.
>> When it shows you that URL?
>> Yeah, look at that.
>> Yeah.
>> So details at four,details five, etc.
Edit, Delete, right?
So that route information foreach individual item
that we are spinningthrough in this for-loop.
>> This for-loop, yeah.
>> These are for-loop right there.
For each item in log.
We're generating more sophisticatedand more complicated ones.
And if we wanted tochange that around,
we would change it atthe routing table.
>> Yup.
>> None of this code would change.
>> None of it changes.
It all stays the same.
And right, we can changethe name of the controller.
We can change the base level.
We can change the pathing ofwhere this thing lives and
all of our anchor tagsjust update automatically.
>> All right, sowhy don't we do this?
Let's try to write ourown custom takeover.
>> Sounds good.
>> All right, so let's go overto the Solution Explorer.
And I'll just stick it inthe root of the application.
I'm gonna say add class, and I'mgonna call it the Repeat TagHelper.
We're gonna make a TagHelperthat will just repeat stuff,
it will be a for loop TagHelper.
>> Sure.
>> Okay, sowe've got Repeat TagHelper,
and I'm going toderive from TagHelper.
And of course it is confused aboutthat, it doesn't know what to do.
I can click on the littleQuick Action here, and it says,
this is a Razor TagHelper.
So I just added that.
There you go.
Just added that usingstatement right there.
>> And we didn't have toadd any extra references.
>> No, that's a good point becauseTagHelpers are fundamental,
TagHelpers are fundamental.
>> They're a part of Razor.
>> They're a part of Razor,and Razor's part of NBC, so
everybody wins.
So the base class TagHelper,of course,
I can right-click on that andsay go to definition.
And we can see what is required forthat base class.
There's the order.
There's Init.
But all we really need tocare about is ProcessAsync.
>> Yeah.
>> And we talked about processversus ProcessAsync a little bit
in the beginner stuff.
But the general idea with async is Ilike to think about it as like I do
it, but do it in a way that doesn'tuse all the resources and wait.
If I told you to go to Chipotle andI did it as a process.
I said, go to Chipotle.
And I just stare atyou until it was done.
Doing it asynchronously,you just call me back.
Let me know whenyou've got my tacos.
>> I might be hanging out there fora little bit, so
I may have to grab a Coke and sit.
>> You may end up not coming back.
So in RepeatTagHelper,I'm gonna say then override, okay?
And it's gonna ask me whichthing I wanna override.
>> Right.
>> And I tell you it's this kind ofIntelliSense stuff that spoils me.
You know what I mean?
>> It does.>> It rots your brain.
I don't know if I could dothis in a Visual Studio code.
>> [LAUGH]>> It's hard work.
I used to be able to do this inNotepad but I'm afraid not anymore.
So here we've got the context forthe TagHelper and then output.
And then the base class herethat says ProcessAsync.
So it's this chain of TagHelpers and
I'm in that largerrendering of Razor stuff.
So what we're gonna dois we're gonna say for-
>> I love that tag completion on
that stuff.
>> Every time, there's so much goodstuff, we're showing real prop.
That's a good one.
[INAUDIBLE] I've gotten sobad with for
that I sometimes forgetthe order of the arguments.
I have to write it by hand.
>> Yeah,that's going on your review.
For, from zero to count.
>> Okay, and we're gonna needto figure out what count is.
We don't have to count right now,okay?
Because we wanna make a repeat andthe repeat is gonna need to count.
So we'll probably need a property.
So, let's go prop, tab, tab, Count.
All right, now we've gotta count.
So you're making an integerproperty on this, and then,
we're gonna exposethat as an attribute.
>> Right.
>> Butattributes in HTML are strings.
>> So this is really cool.
What I like to do when I make myTagHelpers is, I make a comment up
at the top, and I describe whatthe TagHelper is gonna look like.
So I'm imagining that I'mgonna say repeat count = 5,
and then some HTMLhere in the middle.
The TagHelper base class,the TagHelper subsystems can
automatically mapwhat's going on here.
So in this case,count to that property.
It's gonna turn that stringinto an int automatically.
So if I was gonna callthis CountOfThings,
that's the way youwould do it in C#.
The way you would do it inHTML would be like that.
>> They call that what, kabob-case?
>> Yeah, this is kabob, so that'sa funny little side note, right?
So there's Hungarian notation andthere's PascalCasing.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And there's camelCasing,and then there's kabob-casing.
>> Yeah.
>> Isn't that great?
So that people will watch this.
They'll spend an entireday watching this thing.
They'll get no value out of it andthen they're gonna tweet us later.
And they go, that whole thing,not so much, but
the kabob casing, did not know that.
>> [LAUGH]>> Fascinating bit of context there
that we did not have,a little bit of history, okay?
So there's Count.
So then this base here where wecan't return in the middle of that.
>> No.>> Cuz you can't return
in the middle of the for loop, butwe do have this TagHelper output.
So what we're gonna do is we'regonna take that content and
we're just gonna Append the HTML.
Okay, we gonna go andjust say Append, Append, Append.
We're gonna for loop through that.
But what do we wanna do?
Well, we're gonna say repeat, right?
And there is some HTML,not just a little chunk of HTML, but
it could be a whole bunch of stuff.
>> Yeah,anything that's inside this tag.
>> Right, andit could be a deep tree.
>> Sure.>> Going all the way down.
So what we're gonna need to dois get that child's content.
We're gonna have to go andsay, output.
And we'll say GetChildContent but
we're doing it Async cuzit might take awhile.
>> Sure.
>> Okay?>> If there's other stuff
going on there.
>> And if there's caching.
Do we want to use caching?
Do we not wanna use caching?
We gotta think about that as well.
I'll say no, butwe're gonna have to await that.
>> Because it's Async.
>> Because it's Async, okay?
>> Gotcha.
>> All right, so,output await Async.
>> Actually, I think on line 19,
in your signature, I think youneed an Async keyword on that.
>> So, that's a good point.
When I did the override,it popped up the little,
what kind of overridedo you wanna do?
But it did not include the Async,[CROSSTALK] so
that override helper did not know.
So if I hover over this,it's saying well, it's awaitable.
So we can do something about that,so we'll say async.
All right, andthen my squigglies go away.
>> Visual Studio is happy.
>> Okay, so this is inthe namespace WebApplication23.
Will it automaticallybe available to us?
I don't know.
>> I don't think view imports had.
>> Let's find out, let's find out.
I don't know.
This is the thing we were talkingabout in the introductory thing is
that, you can readthe docs all you want.
But ultimately you do haveto experiment for yourself.
>> Sure.
>> So let's get rid of environment,
just for cleanliness sake,actually I'll just do repeat.
So I'm not getting anykind of IntelliSense here.
>> No.
>> All right.>> It doesn't know what repeat is.
>> So let's go back,like you said to view imports.
>> There it is.
>> All right, sohere we'll say addTagHelper,
and it was in WebApplication23.
So I'm basically saying addthe TagHelpers from this project.
>> Yup.
>> Okay, and then we'll close that.
We'll go back over here.
And we'll see if I canget repeat to show up.
So let's see if I have to open andclose that document again.
I don't know.
Maybe I have to re-compile.
Where'd that go?
That was in Movies, okay?
There it is.
>> Interesting, so
in this particular case myIntelliSense, there it is.
So it just took a moment there, yousee, because it's in the background.
>> It wasn't done compiling.
>> It's asynchronously compiling,it's building that stuff up.
But notice as I start typing,
it even lets me knowthat that's available.
So I'm getting IntelliSensecompletion on that, and
look at that.
>> Yeah,there's your count attribute.
>> That right there, let's just zoomin and drink that in for a second.
Cuz this really is the moment forme when I got TagHelpers, right?
>> Sure.
>> I'm in HTML,I'm thinking HTML is convenient.
I'm ready to get an HTML page.
It's suggesting an HTML attribute,and then the tooltip pops up and
says, as a reminder, you know thisis an int, that's a property, right?
>> Yeah.>> It's a really nice
bit of information there.
>> But what happens if youwere to put a string in there?
>> Well, I'm gonna haveto put a string in there.
A string like this?
>> Yeah, if you put five,write F-I-V-E.
>> There you go,that's a great question.
I don't know, let's find out.
I bet you bad thingsare gonna happen.
Oops, let me zoom out andfinish my repeat.
Okay, did it save?
Yes.
>> Visual Studios upsetted us.
>> It doesn't know.
It says, the name five does notexist in a current context.
It's thinking thatfive is a variable.
>> Right.
>> All right, so it's smart.
You are kind of in C# here.
You're in a .NETuniverse at that moment.
>> And if you change it to->> And if you change it to 5,
looks okay.
So let's see if it actually works,though.
Look at that.
>> Yeah, fancy, fancy.
Isn't that good?
So now I can go and do that anywherethings need to be repeated.
If I pick it up and
I move it with a larger scope->> Sure.
>> Things are gonna change.
So being able to write thesethings is super powerful and
people have made someamazing examples of these.
>> There are some veryinteresting ones out there.
>> There was one that you pointed meto that was done by David Paquette,
who is an open source person in MVP.
And he wrote a series ofsample TagHelpers and
they're all open source as well.
>> Yeah, and they're available for
you to add to your project usingthe NuGet Package Manager.
>> So that's interesting,let's grab one of them.
He's got TagHelperSamples.Markdown.
I'm gonna go back overto Visual Studio.
And again, I could addthis in a number of ways.
Some people like to do itin their project.Jason.
>> Mm-hm.>> Some people like to do it
at the command prompt.
Other people like to right-click anddo it within the-
>> Graphically.
>> Graphically within References.
Totally up to you howyou wanna do that.
So we'll go here andI'll put in TagHelperSamples.
There he is.
Hit OK, of course that getsadded to the project.JSON, okay?
>> There it isrestoring the package.
>> Yeah, and this is interesting,
because it has Markdown it's alsogonna bring in a dependency.
>> Another package.
>> Mm-hm, so this particular oneis in TagHelperSamples.Markdown.
So if I remember correctly,I would go over to View Imports and
we would add that, right?
We're gonna add all of them.
Add TagHelper and,what was it, TagHelperSamples?
>> TagHelperSamples.
>> TagHelperSamples,,is it TagHelperSamples to get them,
would I get them all?
Or just the Markdown ones?
Let's do that,let's grab just those.
Cuz the Markdown one is the oneI'm the most excited about.
>> There's a extra quote at the end.
>> Yeah, we can do it with quotes orwithout them, okay?
All right, so those TagHelperSamplesare then added into our project.
There they are.
>> Yep.
>> And if we look at how hisTagHelperSamples work, he's
actually built this great websitewhere you can see them running.
So we'll take some simple markdown,just borrow it from his stuff.
Markdown, of course,
is a way to make HTMLwithout having to write HTML.
>> Yeah.
>> You know how often you have a CMSor something where you have user
input andthey just want to bolt something.
>> Sure.>> But
you don't really feel comfortableputting angle brackets or-
>> No, I don't wanna
have to write HTML.
I wanna be able to use simple,
single keystrokes whileI'm here on my keyboard.
>> Right, so I just dropped that in,
and I'm actually gonnause it as part of repeat.
So we wrote repeat,he wrote markdown.
They're both Tag Helpers,should just work.
>> Make the magic happen, let's see.
>> [LAUGH] No pressure.
>> None.
>> Hit Refresh,we'll have to compile again.
And look at that.>> Look at that.
>> Isn't that nice?
That is just like a taste,just a taste, there's so
much you can do with these.
If you go over to TagHelper Samples,his site,
he's got ones for Bootstrap that canhelp do alerts and things like this.
So you would write alert.
So you're almost writing your own,you're inventing your own HTML.
>> You are, so
he's also then triggeringJavaScript with some of these.
>> Yep,you can do all kinds of things.
He's got divs that match Bootstrap.
It's up to you how far you wantto take these kinds of things.
You can make them assophisticated as you want.
The caching one isquite sophisticated.
All the code is available on GitHub.
>> And I understand thata number of our commercial
control vendors are makingTag Helpers now for ASP.NET Core.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So if you're used to and familiarwith using a grid control from one
of those vendors, or a chartcontrol, there's now Tag Helpers
available that will do the samefunctionality inside ASP.Net Core.
>> Okay, so this isn't a toy, it'snot just little this, little that.
I could actually make an entireJavaScript sortable grid.
Yeah, absolutely.
>> All right.>> Very impressive offerings from
a number of those vendors out there.
>> All right, sothat is Tag Helpers.
It should give you a tasteof what you can do and
where you can get startedon creating Tag Helpers.
We'll take a quick break andwe'll be right back.